<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The increase of popery in England, since the reformation made by King Henry VIII shewing the great encouragement that priests, Jesuits, and other promoter of that bloudy religion have had from persons of power and authority, the discouragements and notorious hardships, even to silencing, and banishment from cities and corporations, that have been the portion of many able and faithful Protestant ministers, that have eminently opposed it : with an essay towards what may possibly befall the Churches of Christ from the hellish contrivances and damnable plots of Romish emissaries : with a faithful extract out of the most authentick records of the most memorable things referring to the reformation, viz. Henry VIII, his reasons given in his proclamation for taking away the Popes usurped power, his protestation against the pope, his injunctions to his clergy, Bishop St[e]phen Gardener's oath or protestation, and his reasons against the Popessupremacy in England and the publick agreement of the whole clergy of England, as confirmed and ratified in the book called the Bishops book, published in the year 1534 / by ..  William Dell ...</title>
            <author>Darrell, William, 1651-1721.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1681</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 160 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 29 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B21152</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing D923</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12730346</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12730346</idno>
            <idno type="VID">200387</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B21152)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 200387)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 980:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The increase of popery in England, since the reformation made by King Henry VIII shewing the great encouragement that priests, Jesuits, and other promoter of that bloudy religion have had from persons of power and authority, the discouragements and notorious hardships, even to silencing, and banishment from cities and corporations, that have been the portion of many able and faithful Protestant ministers, that have eminently opposed it : with an essay towards what may possibly befall the Churches of Christ from the hellish contrivances and damnable plots of Romish emissaries : with a faithful extract out of the most authentick records of the most memorable things referring to the reformation, viz. Henry VIII, his reasons given in his proclamation for taking away the Popes usurped power, his protestation against the pope, his injunctions to his clergy, Bishop St[e]phen Gardener's oath or protestation, and his reasons against the Popessupremacy in England and the publick agreement of the whole clergy of England, as confirmed and ratified in the book called the Bishops book, published in the year 1534 / by ..  William Dell ...</title>
                  <author>Darrell, William, 1651-1721.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 19 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Richard Janeway,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1681.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
                  <note>On t.p.: Intended to be published in the year 1667, but seized at the press by R.L.S. and others.</note>
                  <note>Advertisement precedes t.p.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Henry --  VIII, --  King of England, 1491-1547.</term>
               <term>Catholic Church --  England --  Controversial literature.</term>
               <term>Reformation --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:200387:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>An Advertiſement.</head>
            <p>AT the earneſt requeſt of ſome Friends I have been prevailed with to publiſh this ſmall Treatiſe, which had been ſooner done, had it not been ſeized in the Preſs in the Year <hi>1667;</hi> by which the Reader will eaſily ſee what a proſpect the Author <hi>then</hi> had of the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries we <hi>now</hi> groan under, and with what Zeal he <hi>then</hi> earneſtly laboured to open the eyes of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhmen, againſt the curſed Plots and Contrivan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the bloud-thirſty Papiſts.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>M. D.</signed> 
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>June 18. 1681.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:200387:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE INCREASE OF <hi>Popery in England,</hi> Since the Reformation made by King <hi>Henry</hi> VIII.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>SHEWING</hi> The great encouragement that Prieſts, Jeſuits, and other Promoter. of that bloudy Religion have had from <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of Power and Authority.</hi> The Diſcouragements and notori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Hardſhips, even to Silencing, and Baniſhment from Cities and Corporations, that have been the portion of many able and faithful <hi>Proteſtant Miniſters,</hi> that have eminently oppoſed it. With an Eſſay towards what may poſſibly befall the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of Chriſt from the Helliſh Contrivances and Damnable Plots of <hi>Romiſh Emiſſaries.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>With a faithful Extract out of the moſt Authentick Records of the moſt memorable things referring to the Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, <hi>viz.</hi> King <hi>Henry</hi> VIII. his Reaſons given in his Proclamation for taking away the Popes Uſurped Power. His Proteſtation againſt the Pope. His Injunctions to his Clergy. Biſhop <hi>St phen Gardener</hi>'s Oath or Proteſtation, and his Reaſons againſt the Popes Supremacy in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi> And the publick Agreement of the whole Clergy of <hi>England,</hi> as confirmed and ratified in the Book called <hi>The Biſhops Book,</hi> publiſhed in the Year 1534.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Intended to be publiſhed in the Year</hi> 1667, <hi>but ſeized at the Preſs by</hi> R.L.S. <hi>and others.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>By the late Reverend</hi> William Dell, <hi>ſometime Rector of Yelden in Bedfordſhire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Richard Janeway,</hi> 1681.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:200387:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:200387:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
            <p>FOraſmuch as the great and ſudden growth of <hi>Popery</hi> in theſe three Nations, eſpecially in <hi>England,</hi> (which hath now for a long time, through the Merciful Goodneſs of God, flouriſhed and been happy in the True Reformed <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Religion) is now ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently manifeſt to all who have not either blinded their own Eies, or been blinded by Satan. And foraſmuch as the means whereby this great Miſery and <hi>Myſtery of Iniquity</hi> hath been brought thus far, to this dreadful and unhappy ſucceſs, are alſo as fully manifeſt, to wit:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>First,</hi> The great Countenance and Incouragement that this Heretical and Bloudy Religion hath had from Perſons of Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and Authority, together with all the deteſtable Profeſſors and Promoters thereof, <hi>Papiſts, Prieſts</hi> and <hi>Jeſuites,</hi> who have their daily Councils and Cabals, in the Higheſt Places, to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote this great Deſign of the Devil, and of his Firſt-Born on Earth the <hi>Pope,</hi> even to ſet up the old <hi>Damnable Superſtition and Doctrine of that Man of Sin,</hi> whom the <hi>Weekly Pamphleteer</hi> terms (very devoutly) <hi>His Holineſs,</hi> and yet is no other indeed and truth, than <hi>His Wickedneſs;</hi> the Old Enemy of Chriſt and his true Chriſtians and Followers, the <hi>Son of Perdition;</hi> the Angel of the <hi>Bottomleſs Pit;</hi> the Deſtroyer and Murderer of Souls and Bodies; the impudent <hi>Agent of Hell upon Earth;</hi> the Devils chief Servant and Factor for his Kingdom of Darkneſs; the Monſter of Monſters, who hath abuſed, abaſed and vaſſalized all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian <hi>Princes,</hi> made himſelf ſuperiour to them, yea their very <hi>Lord</hi> and <hi>Maſter</hi> even <hi>in their own Dominions;</hi> who hath inforced all their People, not only by his frivolous Excommunications, but alſo by Fire and Faggot, by Impriſonments, Tortures and all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of exquiſite Cruelties: (which are the only Weapons of his Warfare) to bow down to this <hi>Beaſt,</hi> and to own him as God, ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in the <hi>Temple of God,</hi> not only directly againſt God, but moſt Proudly and Inſolently above him: Who hath pilled and polled them of all their Money and Riches (which is the only Fiſh this great Fiſher of <hi>Rome</hi> fiſhes for) who hath diſturbed, interdict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, diſordered, waſted and overturned whole Empires, King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms and Nations, at his Wicked Pleaſure, and hath been no other through all Ages than Satans eminent Vicegerent upon Earth. This, this prodigious and unparalell'd Wretch, muſt now in the midſt of three <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Nations, be publickly ſtiled
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:200387:3" rendition="simple:additions"/> 
               <hi>His Holineſs</hi> forſooth! who only is holy as Satan is holy; for it may truly be ſaid of him, above any other, <hi>He is of his Father the Devil, and of his works he doth.</hi> I ſay the countenancing of this Damnable <hi>Religion,</hi> and of this <hi>abominable Sect,</hi> and of <hi>the chief H ad</hi> of it, the <hi>Pope,</hi> is one great cauſe of the <hi>new Increaſe</hi> of this <hi>Catholique Her<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> amongſt us.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> Another cauſe is, <hi>The open and notorious diſcountenan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing, diſcouraging, ſilencing, diſplacing and baniſhing from the Chief Cities, and Towns in</hi> England, <hi>all the ab e, faithful, and godly Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters of Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> Who being the diligent, painful and ſincere Teachers of his true Doctrine, ſet forth in his Goſpel for the ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of <hi>Souls,</hi> and for the reducing the <hi>loſt Sheep to the fold of the true Shepherd,</hi> were the greateſt and ſtrongeſt Bulwark againſt <hi>Popery</hi> in the Nation. For <hi>His Wickedneſs,</hi> i. e. the <hi>Pope</hi> and his Wicked Followers, knew well enough that <hi>Popery</hi> could never t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ke root again and proſper in theſe Nations, if theſe Mens Mouths were open. They knew well enough that their dark Doctrine and Kingdom could never prevail, where the clear light of the Goſpel ſhines. And therefore they uſed their chief Artifices and Satanical Subtilties, to ſeduce the Secular <hi>Authority</hi> to run on their Errand, and to do their Drudgery; even to Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs, Impriſon and Baniſh <hi>Theſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> upon ſlight and forged Preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and in their ſtead to foiſt in a number of ignorant, unlearn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, looſe, worldly, profane and debauched Prieſts, in every Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, Town and Pariſh; Men generally, who neither underſtand the Law nor the Goſpel, neither know God nor Themſelves, nor are endued with any ſound and ſerious knowledge of any th ng; that ſo theſe keeping away the Light of the Knowledge of the Truth from the people, they (poor Souls) <hi>might walk in darkn ſs, and not know whither they go,</hi> though they ſhould be led into <hi>Popery</hi> again, which is the Open, Broad Way to Hell.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Another Cauſe is, <hi>The letting looſe the reins to all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r of Ungodlineſs and Unrighteouſn ſs whatſoever,</hi> that Men, not onely without controul, but with countenance, may be as wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as they can be in the World; may Whore, commit Adulte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, Revel, Drink, Swear, Blaſpheme, Reproach the Holy Word of God, Vilifie his Miniſters, Abuſe and Perſecute his People, in the greateſt freedom the Devil can give; whereby Hell is let looſe upon Earth, and the Smoak of the Bottomleſs Pit, that is, Sin and Wickedneſs of all Sorts and Sizes, hath filled and darkened the Nation; and Men are gone to the higheſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent of Wickedneſs that can be practiſed on Earth; that if they would be worſe, they muſt go to Hell in Hell. And that which hath had a Stretched-out Arm to bring about this Kingdom of the Devil amongſt Men, is, the frequent acting and frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Stage-Plays, wherein the moſt Holy and Dreadful Name of God is proſtituted to the Abuſe and Contempt of every baſe Villain; where the Preaching of the Word and Prayer, the High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:200387:3"/> and moſt Sacred Ordinances of God, are ſcorned and jeered in the preſence of great Perſons, where all Vice, and Wickedneſs, and Filthineſs are made <hi>familiar and pl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aſant</hi> to the People. Theſe are the <hi>Nurſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ries</hi> of Hell, and the <hi>Seed-plots</hi> of Damnation, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by moſt of our greateſt Perſons, and of the Gentry are <hi>corrupted, and rendred wholly uſeleſs for any worthy or noble employment in the Commonwealth:</hi> they being through their influence become <hi>brui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh, and without underſtanding, worſe than the Beaſts that periſh, and viler than the Earth.</hi> For the <hi>Pope</hi> knows, that as Chriſt ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers his <hi>Kingdom</hi> here in the <hi>world,</hi> of the <hi>Elect and Faithful;</hi> ſo <hi>his Wickedneſs</hi> muſt gather <hi>his <hi>Kingdom</hi>
               </hi> out of <hi>th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m that periſh,</hi> who have <hi>made ſhipwrack of Faith and good Conſci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nce,</hi> and are throughly practiſed to <hi>commit all inquity with gr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>edineſs.</hi> And now when Men are brought to this ſad paſs, that they are of no Religion at all, but are very Atheiſts, ſo that they can mock at the Name of God, and at his Holy Word, and moſt Bleſſed Spirit, then are they become <hi>ſit Subjects</hi> to receive Antichriſts Religion, which can pleaſe them with Organs and Anthems, and with Vain-Shews, Ceremonies and May-Games, and thereby can ſtifle their unquiet Conſciences: and <hi>He</hi> by his falſe <hi>Pardons</hi> and <hi>Indulgences,</hi> can yet drive them more headlong into Sin; bearing them in hand in the mean time, that though his favour, (which alſo is to be procured by Money) though they commit all theſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bominations, they are notwithſtanding in a fair way to Heaven.</p>
            <p>By which <hi>Catholique Cheat</hi> of his, he deſtroys innumerable Souls of thoſe whom God in his juſt Judgment, <hi>becauſe they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived not the Truth of the Goſpel in the love of it, hath given up to <hi>his</hi> ſtrong deluſions, to believe <hi>his Lyes.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>By theſe <hi>Three Means,</hi> beſides others, things are brought to that paſs, that <hi>Popery</hi> is become the onely <hi>ſafe</hi> and <hi>thriving way;</hi> and thouſands of People whoſe Names are not Written in the Book of Life, ſeeing <hi>ſafety, favour</hi> and <hi>preferments attend it,</hi> run headlong to it, and greedily take Antichriſts <hi>Mark in their Fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head and in their right hand,</hi> for the ſake of preſent <hi>ſecurity and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit,</hi> not conſidering <hi>their latter end.</hi> Yea, they are become ſo tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough and hearty in this their new Undertaking for the <hi>Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique Cauſe,</hi> that through the help they have received by Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney and Arms, together with their ſtrong Incouragements from <hi>Rome,</hi> (which is the chief Wheel in this Motion) they are now ready at a Day and an Hour, when the Watch-Word ſhall be given, (that I may uſe their own word of Myſtery) <hi>To begin their Heats,</hi> that is, to riſe up and deſtroy all that are, or are called <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> of what Degree, Condition, or Sex ſoever, by Fire and Sword, and other Methods of Deſtruction; and not to leave any of their Perſons, or ſo much as their Names, if it may be, to ſurvive in this Nation. This is like to be their firſt attempt, and had been put in Execution before this, if the Lord himſelf, whoſe Eyes behold the Nations, had not moſt graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:200387:4"/> diſappointed them. And their ſecond Deſign, which ſtands behind the Curtain, is like the firſt, to wit, if that ſucceed, then afterwards to <hi>deſtroy all the Engliſh Bloud,</hi> againſt which they have the greateſt Antipathy, and to plant this Land with <hi>French</hi> and other <hi>Foreigners,</hi> that ſo they may throughly reſtore it to its for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer <hi>Popiſh</hi> Splendor, to the great Satisfaction of all <hi>Popiſh Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendom:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Wherefore (if it be poſſible) and if it be the good Pleaſure of the Lord to put a Stop, (and Oh that it might be a full Point and Period!) to theſe Bold Intruſions of Popery, and to all the Cruel Deſigns in the Breaſt of it; it was thought meet for the common utility of all</hi> Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants <hi>and</hi> Engliſhmen, <hi>to repreſent afreſh unto them the Memora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Acts of</hi> Henry <hi>the</hi> VIII. <hi>King of</hi> England, <hi>for the extirpating the</hi> Pope <hi>and his</hi> Curſed Religion, <hi>out of his Dominion. And what He ſaw ſo great cauſe to reject and cast out as Abominable and Intolle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, upon ſuch unanſwerable grounds as He expreſſeth; ſure no man that is in his right Wits, and of a ſound Judgment, hath any just ground to endeavour to bring in again. And this thou thy ſelf, who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever thou art, that art either in the right Faith of a Christian, or in the right Wits of a Man, wilt judge, if thou ſhalt wiſely and impar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tially r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ad, and obſerve what followeth.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="proclamation">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:200387:4"/>
            <head>King <hi>Henry</hi> VIII. his Proclamation for the Aboliſhing the Uſurped Power of the Pope; as it is recorded in <hi>Fox</hi> his Book of Martyrs, <hi>Fol.</hi> 335. <hi>Vol.</hi> 2.</head>
            <p>TRuſty and Well-beloved, We greet you well.<note place="margin">The Kings Proclam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tion againſt the Pope.</note> And whereas not onely upon good, and juſt, and vertuous grounds and reſpects, edified upon the Laws of holy Scripture, dy due conſultation, deliberation, adviſement, and conſent, as well of all other our Nobles and Commons Temporal, as alſo Spiritual, aſſembled in our high Court of Parliament, and by Authority of the ſame, we have by good and wholſom Laws and Statutes made for this purpoſe, extirped, aboliſhed, ſeparated, and ſeclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded out of this our Realm, the Abuſes of the Biſhop of Rome, his Authority and Iuriſdiction of long time uſurp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, as well upon us and our Realm, as upon all other Kings and Princes and their Realms, (like as they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves have confeſſed and affirmed;) but alſo for as much as our ſaid Nobles and Commons, both Spiritual and Temporal, aſſembled in our high Court of Parliament, have upon good, lawful, and vertuous grounds, and for the publick weal of this our Realm, by one whole Aſſent granted, annexed, knit, and united to the Crown Imperial of the ſame, the Title, Dignity,<note place="margin">The Style of <hi>Supreme Head</hi> annexed to the Crown of England.</note> and Style of <hi>Supreme Head or Governour in earth, immediately under God, of the Church of England,</hi> as we be and undoubtedly have hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to been. Which Title and Style both the Biſhops and Elergy of this our Realm have not onely in Convocation aſſembled, conſented, recognized, and approved lawfully and juſtly to appertain unto us, but alſo by Word, Oath, Profeſſion, and Writing under their Signs and Seals, have confeſſed, ratified, corroborated, and confirmed the ſame, utterly renouncing all other Oaths and Obedience to any other forein Potentates, and all forein Iuriſdictions and Powers, as well of the ſaid Biſhop of Rome, as of all other whatſoever they be, as by their ſaid Profeſſions and Writings corroborated with the Subſcription of their Names, and Appenſion of their Seals more plainly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth. We let you to wit, that calling to our remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance the Power, Charge, and Commiſſion given unto us of Almighty God, and upon a vehment love and affection toward our loving and faithful Subjects, perceiving right
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:200387:5"/> well what great reſt, quietneſs, and tranquillity of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, and manifold other commodities might inſurge and ariſe unto them, if that the ſaid Biſhops and other of the Clergy of this our Realm ſhould ſet forth, declare, and preach to them the true and ſyncere Word of God, and without all manner colour, diſſimulation, and hypocriſie, manifeſt and publiſh the great and innumerable Enormi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and Abuſes which the ſaid Biſhop of Rome, as well in the Title and Style, as alſo in Authority and Iuriſdicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, of long time unlawfully and unjuſtly hath uſurped upon us and our Progenitors, and alſo other Chriſtian Princes; have therefore addreſſed our Letters unto the Biſhop of the Diocefe, ſtraitly charging and commanding him in the ſame, that not onely he in his own proper per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon ſhall declare, teach, and preach unto the People, forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with upon the receipt of our ſaid Letters unto him direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, every Sunday and other high Feaſts through the year, the true, mere, and ſyncere Word of God; and that the ſame Title, Style, and Iuriſdiction of Supreme Head appertaineth onely to our Crown and Dignity Royal. Like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe as the ſaid Biſhop, and all other the Biſhops of our Realm, have by Oath affirmed, and confirmed by Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription of their Names, and ſetting to their Seals, but alſo give warning, monition, and charge, to all manner Abbats, Priors, Deans, Archdeacons, Provoſts, Parſons, Vicars, Curats, and all other Eccleſiaſtical Perſons within his ſaid Dioceſe, as well to teach, preach, publiſh, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare, in all manner Churches our aforeſaid juſt Title, Style, and Iuriſdiction, every Sunday and high Feaſt through the year, and further to moniſh and command all other Schoolmaſters within his ſaid Dioceſe, to inſtruct and teach the ſame unto the Children committed unto them; as alſo to cauſe all-manner Prayers, Oriſons, Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bricks, Canons of Maſs-books, and all other Books in the Churches, wherein the ſaid Biſhop of Rome is named, or his preſumptuous and proud Pomp and Authority prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, utterly to be aboliſhed, eradicate, and razed out, and his Name and Memory to be never more (except to his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tumely and reproach) rememb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed,<note place="margin">The Popes Name and Memo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ed.</note> but perpetually ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed and obſcured. And finally to deſiſt and leave out all ſuch Articles as be in the general Sentence, which is uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y accuſtomed to be read, four times in the year, and do tend to the glory and advancement of the Biſhop of Rome, his Name, Title and Iuriſdiction.</p>
            <p>Whereupon we eſteeming and reputing you to be of ſuch ſingular and vehment zeal and affection toward the glory of Almighty God, and of ſo faithful, loving, and obedient heart towards us, as you will not onely do and accompliſh
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:200387:5"/> with all power, wiſdom, diligence, and labour, whatſoever ſhould or might be to the preferment and ſetting forward of Gods Word, but alſo practiſe, ſtudy, and endeavour your ſelf, with all your policy, wit, power, and good will, to am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plifie, defend, and maintain all ſuch Intereſt, Right, Title, Style, Iuriſdiction, and Authority, as is in any wiſe ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertaining unto us, our Dignity, and Prerogative, and Crown Imperial of this our Realm; have thought good and expedient not onely to ſignifie unto you by theſe our Letters the particularities of the Charge, Monition, and Commandment given by us unto the ſaid Biſhop, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is ſpecified, but alſo to require and ſtraitly charge and command you, upon pain of your Allegeance, and as you ſhall avoid our high Indignation and Diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure at your utmoſt peril, laying apart all vain affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, reſpects, or other carnal conſiderations, and ſetting onely before your eyes the mirror of truth, the glory of God, the dignity of your Sovereign Lord and King, and the great concord and unity, and ineſtimable pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit and utility, that ſha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l by the due execution of the premiſſes enſue to your ſelf, and all other faithful and lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Subjects, ye make or cauſe to be made diligent ſearch and wait, and eſpecially in every place of your Shirewick, whether the ſaid Biſhop do truly and ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely, and without all manner cloke, colour, or diſſimu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, execute, and accompliſh our will and command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as is aforeſaid. And in caſe ye ſhall hear, perceive, and approvably underſtand and know, that the ſaid Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop, or any other Eccleſiaſtical Perſon within his Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſe, do omit and leave undone any part or parcel of the premiſſes, or elſe in the execution and ſetting forth of the ſame, do coldly and feignedly uſe any manner ſiniſter addition, wrong interpretation, or painted colour; then we ſtraitly charge and command you, that forthwith upon any ſuch default, negligence, or diſſimulation of the ſaid Biſhop, or any other Eccleſiaſtical Perſon of his Dioceſe, contrary to the true tenour, meaning, and effect of the ſaid Charge by us to him appointed aforeſaid, ye do make in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delayedly, and with all ſpeed and diligence, declaration, and advertiſement, to us and our Council, of the ſaid de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fault, and of the behaviour, manner, and faſhion of the ſame.</p>
            <p>And foraſmuch as we upon ſingular truſt and aſſured confidence which we have in you, and for the ſpecial love and zeal we ſuppoſe and think ye bear toward us and the publick and common Wealth, Vnity, and Tranquillity of this our Realm, have ſpecially elected and choſen you among ſo many for this purpoſe, and have reputed you
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:200387:6"/> ſuch men, as unto whoſe wiſdom, diſcretion, truth, and fide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, we might commit a matter of ſuch great weight, mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and importance, as whereupon the Vnity and Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quillity of our Realm doth conſiſt. If ye ſhould contrary to our expectation and truſt which we have in you, and againſt your duty and Allegeance towards us, neglect or omit to do with all your diligence and wiſdom, whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſhall be in your power, for the due performance of our mind and pleaſure to you before declared in this behalf, or halt or ſtumble at any part or ſpecialty of the ſame; be ye aſſured that we like a Prince of Iuſtice will ſo extremely puniſh you for the ſame, that all the World beſides ſhall take by you example and beware, contrary to their Alie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance, to diſobey the lawful Commandment of their So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereign Lord and Prince in ſuch things, as by the faithful execution whereof, ye ſhall not onely advance the Honour of Almighty God, and ſet forth the Majeſty and Imperial Dignity of your Sovereign Lord, but alſo bring an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſtimable weal, profit, and commodity, unity and tranquil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity to all the common State of this our Realm, whereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to both by the Laws of God, Nature, and Man, ye be ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly bound.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Given under our Signet at our Palace of Weſtminſter,</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>the 9. day of June.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <postscript>
               <p>Furthermore, that no man ſhall cavil or ſurmiſe this fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal fall and ruine of the Pope to have come raſhly upon the Kings own partial affection, or by any ſenſual temerity of a few, and not by the grave and adviſed Iudgment, Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation, and Conſent, generally and publickly, as well of the Nobles and Commons Temporal, as alſo upon ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantial grounds, and the very ſtrength of truth by the diſcuſſion and conſultation of the Spiritual and moſt Learned Perſons in this Realm. It ſhall be requiſite moreover to theſe premiſſes, to adjoyn the words and teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies alſo of the Biſhops own oaths and profeſſion made to the King, yielding and rendering unto him onely the Style of <hi>Supreme Head next under Chriſt of the Church of England;</hi> all other Service, Subjection, and Obedience to be given to any other forein Potentate, which ſhould be prejudicial to the Kings Highneſs in this behalf being ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded, and that both frankly and freely of their own volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary motion, and alſo upon the faith and fidelity of their Prieſthood, as by their own words and handwriting may appear, in form as hereunder followeth.</p>
            </postscript>
         </div>
         <div type="oath">
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:200387:6"/>
            <head>The Oath of <hi>Stephen Gardener</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Wincheſter,</hi> made to King <hi>Henry</hi> VIII.</head>
            <div xml:lang="lat" type="version">
               <p>EGO Stephanus Wintonienſis Epiſcopus, pure, ſponte,<note place="margin">The Oath of <hi>Stephen Garde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner</hi> to the King.</note> &amp; abſolute, in verbo Pontificio, profiteor ac ſpondeo illuſtriſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mae veſtrae Regiae Majeſtati, ſingulari ac ſummo Domino meo &amp; Patrono, Henrico Dei gratia Angliae &amp; Franciae Regi, Fidei De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſori, Domino Hiberniae, atque in terris Eccleſiae Anglicanae Supremo immediate ſub Chriſto Capiti, quod poſthac nulli ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terno Imperatori, Regi, Principi, aut Praelato, nec Romano Pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifiei (quem Papam vocant) fidelitatem &amp; obedientiam, &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div xml:lang="eng" type="version">
               <head>Tranſlated into <hi>Engliſh</hi> thus.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>I Stephen</hi> Biſhop of Wincheſter, do purely of mine own voluntary accord, and abſolutely in the word of a Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop, profeſs and promiſe to your Princely Majeſty, my ſingular and chief Lord and Patron, <hi>Henry</hi> the Eighth, by the grace of God King of England and of France, Defender of the Faith, Lord of Ireland, and in earth of the Church of England Supreme Head immediately under Chriſt; That from this day forward I ſhall ſwear, promiſe, give, or cauſe to be given, to no forein Potentate, Emperour, King, Prince, or Prelate, nor yet to the Biſhop of Rome, whom they call Pope, any Oath or Fealty directly or indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly, either by word or writing; but at all times, and in every caſe and condition, I ſhall obſerve, hold, and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, to all effects and intents, the quarrel and cauſe of your Royal Majeſty and your Succeſſors, and to the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termoſt of my power ſhall defend the ſame againſt all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of perſons, whomſoever I ſhall know or ſuſpect to be Adverſaries to your Majeſty, or to your Succeſſors; and ſhall give my faith, truth, and obedience, ſyncerely and with my very heart, onely to your Royal Majeſty as to my Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Prince. I profeſs the Papacy of Rome not to be or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained of God by holy Scripture,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Stephen Garde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner</hi> abrenoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth the Pope.</note> but conſtantly do affirm and openly declare, and ſhall declare it, to be ſet up onely by Man, and ſhall cauſe diligently other men likewiſe to publiſh the ſame. Neither ſhall I enter any Treaty with any perſon or perſons, either privily or apertly, or ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent thereto, that the Biſhop of Rome ſhall have or exerciſe here any Authority or Iuriſdiction, or is to be reſtored to any Iuriſdiction hereafter.</p>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:200387:7"/>
               <p>Furthermore, that the ſaid Biſhop of Rome now being, or any that ſhall ſucc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed him hereafter in the ſaid See, is not to be called Pope, nor Supreme Biſhop, or Vniverſal Biſhop, nor moſt holy Lord, but onely ought to be called Biſhop of Rome, and Fellow Brother, (as the old manner of the moſt ancient Biſhops hath been.) This I ſhall to my power openly maintain and defend.</p>
               <p>And I ſhall firmly obſerve, and cauſe to be obſerved of other, to the uttermoſt of my cunning, wit, and power, all ſuch Laws and Acts of this Realm, how and whatſoever, as have been enacted and eſtabliſhed for the extirpation and ſuppreſſion of the Papacy, and of the Authority and Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction of the ſaid Biſhop of Rome. Neither ſhall I appeal hereafter to the ſaid Biſhop of Rome, nor ever con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to any perſon that ſhall appeal to him; neither ſhall I attempt, proſecute, or follow any Suit in the Court of Rome, for any cauſe of right or juſtice to be had, or ſhall make anſwer to any Plea or Action, nor ſhall take upon me the perſon and office either of the Plaintiff or Defendent in the ſaid Court. And if the ſaid Biſhop by his Meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, or by his Letters, ſhall make any means or ſignifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion unto me, of any matter whatſoeuer it be, I ſhall with all ſpeed and diligence make declaration and advertiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment thereof, or cauſe the ſame to be ſignified either to your Princely Majeſty, or to ſome of your ſecret Council, or to your Succeſſors, or any of their privy Council. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhall I ſend or cauſe to be ſent at any time any wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting or meſſenger to the ſaid Biſhop or to his Court, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the knowledge or conſent of your Majeſty or your Succeſſors, willing me to ſend writing or meſſenger unto him. Neither ſhall I procure or give counſel to any per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to procure Bulls, Briefs, or Reſcripts whatſoever, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for me or for any other, from the ſaid Biſhop of Rome or his Court. And if any ſuch ſhall be procured againſt my will and knowledge, either in general or in ſpecial, or elſe howſoever they ſhall be granted unto them, I ſhall ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and diſcloſe the ſame, and not conſent thereunto, nor uſe them in any caſe, and ſhall cauſe them to be brought to your Majeſty or your Succeſſors.</p>
               <p>Furthermore, for the confirmation hereof I give my faith and truth by firm promiſe, and in the faith of a Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop, that againſt this my foreſaid Profeſſion and Promiſe made I ſhall defend my ſelf by no Diſpenſation, Excepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, nor any remedy or cautel of Law or Example, during this my natural life. And if heretofore I have done or made any Proteſtation in prejudice of this my Profeſſion and Promiſe here made, the ſame I do revoke at this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, and for ever hereafter, and here utterly do renounce
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:200387:7"/> by theſe preſents. Whereunto I have ſubſcribed and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derwritten the name both of my ſelf and of my Biſhop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rick with my proper hand, and thereto alſo have put to my Seal, in perpetual and undoubted teſtimony of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſes.</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>
                     <date>
                        <hi>Given the tenth day of February, Anno 1534, and of our So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereign Lord King Henry the eight twenty ſix.</hi>
                     </date>
                  </dateline>
                  <signed>Stephanus Wintonienſis.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="reasons">
            <head>The ſame Biſhop of <hi>Wincheſter</hi>'s Reaſons againſt the Pope's Supremacy.</head>
            <p>MOreover the ſaid <hi>Gardener</hi> in the forenamed Book <hi>De vera Obedientia,</hi> what Conſtancy he pretendeth,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Steph. Wint.</hi> a Lutheran in his Book <hi>De vera obedientia.</hi>
               </note> what Arguments he inferreth, how earneſtly and pithily he diſputeth on the Kings ſide againſt the Vſurped State of the Biſhop of Romes Authority, by the words of his Book it may appear; whereof a brief Collection here fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth.</p>
            <p>IN the proceſs of his foreſaid Book,<note place="margin">The Sword of the Church how far it ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendeth.</note> he alledging the old diſtinction of the Papiſts, wherein they give to the Prince the Regiment of things Temporal, and to the Church of things Spiritual; comparing the one to the greater Light, the other to the leſſer Light, he confuteth and derideth the ſame diſtinction, declaring the Sword of the Church to extend no further, than to Teaching and Excommunication, and referreth all preheminence to the Sword of the Prince; alledging for this the ſecond Pſalm, <hi>And now you Kings be wiſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal 2.</note> 
               <hi>and be learned ye that judge the earth, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Alſo the example of <hi>Salomon,</hi> who being a King,<note place="margin">2 Par. 28.</note> 
               <hi>accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to his Fathers appointment ordained the Offices of the Prieſts in their Miniſteries, and Levites in their Order,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod. 32.</note> 
               <hi>that they might give thanks and miniſter before the Prieſts, after the order of every day, and Porters in their diviſions gate by gate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſpeaking more of the ſaid <hi>Salomon</hi> he ſaith,<note place="margin">1 Reg. 22.</note> 
               <hi>For ſo commanded the Man of God, neither did the Prieſts nor Levites omit any thing of all that he had commanded, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Beſides this, he alledgeth alſo the example of King <hi>Eze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chias,</hi> 2 <hi>Paralyp.</hi> 28. He alledgeth moreover the example and fact of <hi>Juſtinian,</hi> which made Laws touching the Faith, Biſhops, Clerks, Hereticks, and ſuch other.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:200387:8"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Aaron</hi> (ſaith he) obeyed <hi>Moſes, Salomon</hi> gave ſentence upon <hi>Abiathar</hi> the High Prieſt.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">1 Macch. 10. 1 Macch. 14.</note>
               <hi>Alexander</hi> the King (in the firſt of <hi>Macchabees</hi>) writeth thus to <hi>Jonathas, Now have we made thee this day the High Prieſt of thy people, &amp;c.</hi> So did <hi>Demetrius</hi> to <hi>Simon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Then coming to the words of <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſpoken to <hi>Peter, Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew</hi> 16.<note place="margin">Matth. 16.</note> upon which words the Pope pretendeth to build all his Authority, to this he anſwereth, That if Chriſt by thoſe words had limited to <hi>Peter</hi> any ſuch ſpecial ſtate or preheminence above all Princes, then were it not true that is written, <hi>Coepit Jeſus docere &amp; facere;</hi> foraſmuch as the words of Chriſt ſhould then be contrary to his own facts and example, who in all his life never uſurped either in himſelf any ſuch domination above Princes, ſhewing him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf rather ſubject unto Princes; nor yet did ever permit to his Apoſtles any ſuch example of ambition to be ſeen, but rather rebuked them for ſeeking any manner of Majority amongſt them.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The Kings Style and Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle approved by <hi>Steph. Wint.</hi>
               </note>And where he reaſoneth of the Kings Style and Title, being called the King of England and of France, Defender of the Faith, Lord of Ireland, and Supreme Head in earth of the Church of England immediately under Chriſt, &amp;c. thus he addeth his mind and cenſure, ſaying, That he ſeeth no cauſe in this Title why any man ſhould be offend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that the King is called the Head of the Church of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, rather than of the Realm of England; and addeth his reaſon thereunto, ſaying, If the Prince and King of England be the Head of his Kingdom, that is, of all Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhmen that be his Subjects, is there any cauſe why the ſame Engliſh Subjects ſhould not be ſubject to the ſame Head likewiſe, in this reſpect becauſe they are Chriſtians, that is to ſay, for the title of Godlineſs, as though that God, which is the cauſe of all Obedience, ſhould now be the cauſe of Rebellion?</p>
            <p>At length thus he concludeth with an Exclamation ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, To ſay (ſaith he) that a King is the Head of a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and not of the Church, what an abſurd and a fooliſh ſaying is this?</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The King is as well the Head of the Church as of his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom.</note>And further, adding for example the ſubjection of the Servant and Wife. If the Servant (ſaith he) be ſubject to his Maſter, or Wife to her Husband, being Infidels, doth their Converſion afterward, or name of Chriſtians, make them leſs Subjects than they were before? As Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion therefore doth not alter the Authority of the Maſter over the Servant, nor of the Husband over the Wife; no more (ſaith he) doth it between the Prince and Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:200387:8"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Paul</hi> making no exception nor diſtinction of Subjection, ſave onely of that which belongeth to God, willeth all men to obey their Princes; and what Princes? Thoſe Prin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ces which bear the ſword. And although we are bound by the Scripture to obey our Biſhops and Spiritual Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors of the Church, yet that obedience diminiſheth nothing the chief and head Authority that ought to be given to the Prince, no more than the obedience of the Servant to his Maſter, or of the Wife to her Husband, exempteth them from Subjection due to their Superiour Powers.</p>
            <p>And herewithall he inferreth a principle of the Law;<note place="margin">A Rule of the Law.</note> Divers Iuriſdictions (ſaith he) proceeding from one perſon do not marry nor hinder themſelves, but rather do con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm and fortifie one another.</p>
            <p>Again, whereas the Biſhop of Rome under the name of <hi>Peter</hi> doth appropriate to himſelf the higheſt place in the Church, for that he is the Succeſſor of <hi>Peter.</hi> Thereunto he anſwereth in one word, but in that one word he an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwereth enough and to the full; I would (ſaith he) he were,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Wencheſters</hi> with that the Pope were <hi>Peters</hi> Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſor.</note> for ſo in very deed he might well exceed and paſs all Kings and Princes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> if not in preheminency of Dignity, yet in ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miration and excellency of Virtue; in which kind of ſupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riority the Lord Chriſt would his Apoſtles and Miniſters to go before all Kings and Emperours in the whole world.</p>
            <p>After this, in proſecuting the Argument of <hi>Peters</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, he argueth thus and ſaith;<note place="margin">Argument: The Preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive was gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to him which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed. Fleſh and Bloud in <hi>Peter</hi> did not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs Chriſt. <hi>Ergo</hi> the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogative was not given to the Fleſh and Bloud of <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r.</hi>
               </note> that as fleſh and bloud did not reveal to <hi>Peter</hi> that Confeſſion, ſo neither was that Prerogative given to the fleſh and bloud of <hi>Peter,</hi> but to the better part, that is, to the ſpirit of <hi>Peter,</hi> which is to mean, in reſpect of the ſpiritual Confeſſion of <hi>Peter,</hi> and not in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of any carnal place or perſon, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item,</hi> If the Scholar ought not to be above the Maſter, how then could either <hi>Peter</hi> take that upon him, which Chriſt his Maſter ſo conſtantly did refuſe? Or how can the Biſhop of Rome now claim that by Succeſſion, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of no example is to be found either in the Head, or his Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceſſor before him? For ſo we read in <hi>Euſebius,</hi> both of <hi>Peter, James,</hi> and <hi>John,</hi> that they did arrogate no ſuch Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy unto them, but were content that <hi>James</hi> ſurnamed <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus</hi> ſhould be the Biſhop of the Apoſtles.</p>
            <p>And as for the name and ſignification of the word <hi>Prima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus, i.</hi> Primacy,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>matus</hi> or Primacy what it ſignifieth.</note> if it be taken for the firſt nomination, or the firſt place given, ſo he granteth that <hi>Peter</hi> had the prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the firſt name and place in the order of the Apoſtles; but it followeth not, that with this Primacy he had alſo a Kingdom given.<note place="margin">He ſaith, <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm thy Breth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren,</hi> but not thy Subjects.</note> And though he were bid of the Lord to confirm his Brethren, yet was he not bid to exerciſe an Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery upon his Brethren, for ſo were they not his Brethren but his Subjects.</p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:200387:9"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Primus Prima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus, i.</hi> Primacy meaneth as much as the firſt ſtanding in Vocation, and is the name of Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue and not of Power.</note>That <hi>Peter</hi> was <hi>Primus,</hi> that is, firſt or chief in the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of them which confeſſed Chriſt, it is not to be denied; for firſt he confeſſed, firſt he taught the Iews, firſt he ſtood in defence of the Verity, and was the firſt and chief Prolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutor among them; but yet that maketh not that he ſhould therefore vindicate a general Primacy and Rule over all other States and Potentates of the world, no more than <hi>Apelles,</hi> becauſe he is noted the firſt and chief of all Paint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, therefore ought to bear rule over all Painters; or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Vniverſity of Paris is nominate for the firſt and chief of other Vniverſities, ſhall therefore the French King and all other Princes, in their publick Adminiſtration wherein they are ſet of God, become Subjects and Vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings to that Vniverſity?</p>
            <p>Thus after many other reaſons and perſuaſions contain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the ſaid Book <hi>De obedientia,</hi> (for I do but ſuperficially skim over the top onely of his Probations and Arguments) finally in the end of his Peroration he concludeth the whole ſumm of his mind in this effect; firſt denying that the Biſhop of Rome had ever any ſuch extern Iuriſdiction aſſigned to him abſolutely from God, to reign over Kings and Princes; for the probation whereof he hath alledged ſufficiently (as he ſaith) the examples and doings of Chriſt himſelf, which ought to be to us all a ſufficient Docu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>And as concerning the term of Primacy, albeit it be uſed ſometimes of the Fathers, yet the matter being well conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered and rightly expounded, maketh nothing for the large Dominion of the Biſhop of Rome, which now he doth uſurp.</p>
            <p>Alſo as for the Prerogatives granted unto <hi>Peter,</hi> by the which Prerogatives our Saviour would crown his own Gifts given unto him, crowning not the fleſh and bloud of <hi>Peter,</hi> but the marvellous teſtimony of his Confeſſion, all this maketh nothing for the Popes purpoſe.</p>
            <p>Likewiſe as concerning the Local Succeſſion of <hi>Peter,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Succeſſion of <hi>Peter.</hi>
               </note> the Pope hath nothing thereby to claim. If he will be Succeſſor of <hi>Peter,</hi> he muſt ſucceed him in Faith, Doctrine, and Conditions; and in ſo doing he neither will, neither yet ſhall need to ſeek for Honour, but ſhall be honoured of all good men, according as a good man ſhould be, and that much more than he being a good man would require.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Steph. Wint.</hi> takes his <hi>Vale</hi> of the Pope, but not his <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ltimum Vale.</hi>
               </note>And thus <hi>Stephen Wincheſter</hi> taking his leave, and bid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the Pope farewell, endeth with a friendly Exhortati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, willing him to be wiſe and circumſpect, and not to ſtrive ſtubbornly againſt the truth. The light of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel (ſaith he) ſo ſpreadeth his beams in all mens eyes, that the works of the Goſpel be known, the Myſteries of
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:200387:9"/> Chriſts Doctrine are opened, both learned and unlearned Men and Women, being Engliſh born, do ſee and perceive that they have nothing to do with Rome, nor with the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of Rome, but that every Prince in his own Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is to be taken and accepted as a Vicar of God, and Vice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerent of Chriſt in his own bounds. And therefore ſeeing this Order is taken of God, and one in the Church ſhould bear the Office of Teaching,<note place="margin">The Office of Teaching.</note> another ſhould bear the Office of Ruling,<note place="margin">The Office of Ruling.</note> (which Office is onely limited to Princes) he exhorteth him to conſider the truth, and to follow the fame, wherein conſiſteth our true and ſpecial Obedience, &amp;c.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>A Letter of the Univerſity of <hi>Cambridge</hi> againſt the Uſurped Power of the Biſhop of <hi>Rome.</hi>
            </head>
            <div xml:lang="lat" type="version">
               <p>UNiverſis Sanctae Matris Eccleſiae filiis, ad quos praeſentes Literae perventurae ſunt, coetus omnis regentium &amp; non regentium Academiae Cantabrigienſis, ſalutem, in omnium ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vatore Jeſu Chriſto.</p>
               <p>Cum de Romani Pontificis poteſtate, &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div xml:lang="eng" type="version">
               <head>Tranſlated into <hi>Engliſh</hi> thus.</head>
               <p>TO all and ſingular Children of the holy Mother Church, to whoſe hands theſe preſents ſhall come,<note place="margin">A Letter of the Univerſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <hi>Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge.</hi>
                  </note> the whole Society of Regents and not Regents of the Vniver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of Cambridge, ſendeth greeting in our Saviour Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
               <p>Whereas now of late it hath riſen up in queſtion among us concerning the Power of the Biſhop of Rome, which he doth both claim to himſelf by the holy Scripture, over all Provinces and Nations in Chriſtendom, and hath now of long time exerciſed in this Realm of England: And foraſmuch as our Cenſure concerning the cauſe is requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, to wit, Whether the Biſhop of Rome hath any Power or Authority in this Kingdom of <hi>England</hi> allotted to him by God in the Scripture, more than any other forein Biſhop, or no? We thought it therefore good reaſon, and our duty for the ſearching out of the verity of the ſaid Queſtion, that we ſhould imploy therein our whole endeavour and ſtudy, whereby we might tender and publiſh to the world what our reaſon and cenſure is touching the premiſſes.
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:200387:10"/> For therefore we ſuppoſe that Vniverſities were firſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided and inſtituted of Princes, to the end that doth the people of Chriſt might in the Law of God be inſtructed, and alſo that falſe Errors (if any did riſe) might through the vigilant care and induſtry of learned Divines be diſcuſſed, extinguiſhed and utterly rooted out. For the which cauſe we in our Aſſemblies and Convocations (after our accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomed manner) reſorting<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and conferring together upon the Queſtion aforeſaid, and ſtudiouſly debating and delibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rating with our ſelves, how and by what order we might beſt proceed for the finding out of the truth of the matter; and at length chooſing out certain of the beſt learned Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors and Batchelors of Divinity, and other Maſters, have committed to them in charge, ſtudiouſly to inſearch and peruſe the places of holy Scripture, by the viewing and conferring of which places together, they might certifie us what is to be ſaid to the Queſtion propounded.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The Cenſure of the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity of <hi>Cambridge</hi> againſt the Popes Supre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy.</note>Foraſmuch therefore as we having heard and well advi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and throughly diſcuſſed in open Diſputations, what may be ſaid on both parts of the foreſaid Queſtion, thoſe Reaſons and Arguments do appear to us more probable, ſtronger, truer, and more certain, and ſounding much more near to the pure and native ſenſe of Scripture, which do deny the Biſhop of Rome to have any ſuch power given him of God in the Scripture. By reaſon and force of which Arguments we being perſuaded, and conjoyning together in one Opinion, have with our ſelves thus decreed to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer unto the Queſtion aforeſaid, and in theſe writings thus reſolutely do anſwer in the name of the whole Vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity, and for a Concluſion undoubted do affirm, approve, and pronounce,<note place="margin">The Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> hath no more State in <hi>England</hi> than hath any other Biſhop.</note> That the Biſhop of Rome hath no more State, Authority, and Iuriſdiction given him of God in the Scriptures over this Realm of England, than any other extern Biſhop hath. And in teſtimony and credence of this our Anſwer and Affirmation, we have cauſed our common Seal to be put to theſe our foreſaid Letters ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly.</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>
                     <hi>At Cambridge in our Regent Houſe,</hi> 
                     <date>
                        <hi>Anno Dom.</hi> 1534.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="agreement">
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:200387:10"/>
            <head>The publick and general Agreement of the whole Clergy of <hi>England,</hi> confirmed and ratified in their own publick Book called <hi>The Biſhops Book, Anno</hi> 1534. with the Names of the Witneſſes.</head>
            <p>WE think it convenient,<note place="margin">Te<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>timonies out o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops Book againſt the Popes Supre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy.</note> that all Biſhops and Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers ſhall inſtruct and teach the People commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted unto their ſpiritual charge, that whereas certain men do imagine and affirm, that Chriſt ſhould give unto the Biſhop of Rome power and authority, not onely to be Head and Governour of all Prieſts and Biſhops in Chriſts Church, but alſo to have and occupy the whole Monarchy of the World in his hands, and that he may thereby law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully depoſe Kings and Princes from their Realms, Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions, and Seigniories, and ſo transfer and give the ſame to ſuch perſons as him liketh, that is utterly falſe and untrue; for Chriſt never gave unto S. <hi>Peter,</hi> or unto any of the Apoſtles or their Succeſſors, any ſuch Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. And the Apoſtles S. <hi>Peter</hi> and S. <hi>Paul</hi> do teach and command, that all Chriſtian People, as well Prieſts and Biſhops, as others, ſhould be obedient and ſubject unto the Princes and Potentates of the World, although they were Infidels.</p>
            <p>And as for the Biſhop of Rome, it was many hundred years after Chriſt before he could acquire or get any Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy or Governance above any other Biſhops out of his Province in Italy; ſince the which time he hath ever uſurped more and more. And though ſome part of his power was given to him by the conſent of the Emperours, Kings and Princes, and by the conſent alſo of the Clergy in General Councils aſſembled; yet ſurely he attain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the moſt part thereof by marvellous ſubtilty and craft,<note place="margin">How the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> roſe by ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> and eſpecially by colluding with great Kings and Princes, ſometime training them into his Devotion by pretence and colour of Holineſs and Sanctimony, and ſometime con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraining them by force and tyranny. Whereby the ſaid Biſhops of Rome aſpired and roſe at length unto ſuch greatneſs in Strength and Authority, that they preſumed and took upon them to be Heads,<note place="margin">Concilium ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tium Cartha i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nenſe cap. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> and to put Laws by their own Authority, not onely unto all other Biſhops within Chriſtendom, but alſo unto the Emperours, Kings, and other the Princes and Lords of the world, and that under
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:200387:11"/> the pretence of the Authority c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>mit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted unto them by the Goſpel;<note place="margin">
                  <p>Firſt, the General Council of <hi>Nice</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creed, that the Patriarchs of <hi>Alexandria</hi> and <hi>Antiochia</hi> ſhould have like power over the Countries about thoſe Cities, as the Biſhops of <hi>Rome</hi> had over the Countries about <hi>Rome.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>In the Council of <hi>Milevitan</hi> it was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creed, that if a Clerk of <hi>Africk</hi> would ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal out of <hi>Africk</hi> un<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o any Biſhop be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the Sea, he ſhould be taken as a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon Excommunicate.</p>
                  <p>In the General Council of <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> the firſt it was likewiſe decreed, that eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Cauſe between any perſons ſhould be determined within the Provinces where the matters did lie; and that no Biſhop ſhould exerciſe any power out of his own Dioceſe or Province. And this was alſo the mind of holy S. <hi>Cyprian,</hi> and of other holy men of <hi>Africa.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>To conclude, therefore the Pope hath no ſu h Primacy g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ven him, either by the words of Scripture, or by any General Council, or by common conſent of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>holick Church.</p>
               </note> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>rein the ſaid Biſhops of Rome do no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> nely abuſe and pervert the true ſenſe and meaning of Chriſts Word, but they do alſo clean contrary to the uſe and cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom of the Primitive Church, and ſo do manifeſtly violate as well the holy Canons made in the Church immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately after the time of the Apoſtles, as alſo the Decrees and Conſtitutions made in that behalf by the holy Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of the Catholick Church aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled in the firſt General Councils. And finally, they do tranſgreſs their own profeſſion made in their Creation. For all the Biſhops of Rome always, when they be conſecrated and made Biſhops of that See, do make a ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn profeſſion and vow, that they ſhall inviolably ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve and keep all the Ordinances made in the firſt eight General Councils; among the which it is ſpecially provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded and enacted, that all Cauſes ſhall be finiſhed and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined within the Province where the ſame begun, and that by the Biſhops of the ſame Province, and that no Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop ſhall exerciſe any Iuriſdiction out of his own Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince:<note place="margin">Gregorius l. <hi>4.</hi> Epiſtolarum indictione <hi>13.</hi> Epiſt <hi>13.</hi>
               </note> and divers ſuch other Canons were then made and confirmed by the ſaid Councils to repreſs and take away out of the Church all ſuch Primacy and Iuriſdiction over Kings and Biſhops, as the Biſhops of Rome pretend now to have over the ſame. And we find that divers good Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, Biſhops of Rome, did greatly reprove, yea and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hor (as a thing clean contrary to the Goſpel, and the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees of the Church) that any Biſhop of Rome, or elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where, ſhould preſume, uſurp, or take upon him the Title and Name of Vniverſal Biſhop, or of the Head of all Prieſts, or of the Higheſt Prieſt, or any ſuch like Title. For confirmation whereof it is out of all doubt, that there is no mention made neither in Scripture, nor in the Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings of any authentical Doctor or Author of the Church, being within the time of the Apoſtles, that Chriſt did ever make or inſtitute any diſtinction or difference to be in the preheminence of Power, Order, or Iuriſdiction, between the Apoſtles themſelves, or between the Biſhops themſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ves, but that they were all equal in Power, Order, Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, and Iuriſdiction. And that there is now, and ſince the time of the Apoſtles, any ſuch diverſity or differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence among the Biſhops, it was deviſed by the antient Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:200387:11"/> of the Primitive Church, for the conſervation of good order and unity of the Catholick Church, and that either by the conſent and authority, or elſe at the leaſt by the permiſſion and ſufferance of the Princes and Civil Powers for the time ruling, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>And ſhortly after followeth, And for the better confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of this part, we think it alſo convenient that all Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops and Preachers ſhall inſtruct and teach the people committed unto their ſpiritual charge, that Chriſt did by expreſs words prohibit, that none of his Apoſtles, nor any of their Succeſſors, ſhould, under the pretence of the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority given unto them by Chriſt, take upon them the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of the Sword; that is to ſay, the Authority of Kings, or of any Civil Power in this world, yea or any Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority to make Laws or Ordinances in cauſes appertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing unto Civil Powers. Truth it is, the Prieſts and Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops may execute all ſuch Temporal Power and Iuriſdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as is committed unto them by the Ordinance and Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of Kings, or other Civil Powers, and by the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of the people, (as Officers and Miniſters under the ſaid Kings and Powers) ſo long as it ſhall pleaſe the ſaid Kings and People to permit and ſuffer them ſo to uſe and execute the ſame. Notwithſtanding if any Biſhop, of what eſtate or dignity ſoever he be, be he Biſhop of Rome, or of any other City, Province, or Dioceſe, do preſume to take upon him Authority or Iuriſdiction in cauſes or mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters which appertain unto Kings, and the civil powers and their Courts, and will maintain or think that he may ſo do by the Authority of Chriſt and his Goſpel, although the Kings and Princes would not permit and ſuffer him ſo to do; no doubt that Biſhop is not worthy to be called a Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop, but rather a Tyrant,<note place="margin">The Biſhop oſ <hi>Rone</hi> judged to be a Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant and U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurper.</note> and as Vſurper of other mens rights contrary to the Law of God, and is worthy to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted none otherwiſe than he that goeth about to ſubvert the Kingdom of Chriſt. For the Kingdom of Chriſt in his Church is a ſpiritual, and not a carnal Kingdom of the world; that is to ſay, the very Kingdom that Chriſt by him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf or by his Apoſtles and Diſciples ſought here in this world, was to bring all Nations from the carnal King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of the Prince of darkneſs unto the light of his ſpiritual Kingdom, and ſo himſelf to reign in the hearts of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple by grace, faith, hope, and charity. And therefore <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ith Chriſt did never ſeek nor exerciſe any worldly Kingdom or Dominion in this world, but rather refuſing and flying from the ſame, did leave the ſaid worldly Governance of Kingdoms, Realms, and Nations, to be governed by Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and Potentates, (in like manner as he did find them) and commanded alſo his Apoſtles and Diſciples to do the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:200387:12"/> ſemblable, as it was ſaid before; whatſoever Prieſt or Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop will arrogate or preſume to take upon him any ſuch Authority, and will pretend the Authority of the Goſpel for his defence therein, he doth nothing elſe but (in a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner as you would ſay) crowneth Chriſt again with a Crown of Thorn, and traduceth and bringeth him forth again with his Mantle of Purple upon his back, to be mocked and ſcorned of the world, as the Iews did to their own dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation.</p>
            <p>This Doctrine was ſubſcribed and allowed by the wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and teſtimony of theſe Biſhops and other Learned Men, whoſe Names hereunder follow, as appeareth in the Biſhops Book before named.</p>
            <list>
               <head>TESTES.</head>
               <item>
                  <note place="margin">Teſtimonies of Bi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hops and Doctors of <hi>England</hi> againſt the Pope.</note>
                  <hi>Thomas Cantuarienſis</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Edouardus Eboracenſis</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Johannes Londonenſis</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Cuthbertus Dunelmenſis</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Stephanus W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ntonlenſis</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Robertus Carliolenſis</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Johannes Exonienſis</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Johannes Lincolnienſis</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Johannes Bathonienſis</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Rolandus Coventr. &amp; Lichfield.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Thomas Elienſis</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Nicolaus Sarum</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Johannes Bangor.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Edouardus Herefordienſis</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Hugo Wigornienſis</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Johannes Roffenſis</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Richardus Ciceſtrenſis</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Gulielmus Menevenſis</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Robertus Aſſavenſis</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Robertus Landavenſis</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Guilielmus Norwicenſis</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Richardus Wolman Archidia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con. Sudbur.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Guilielmus Knight Archidia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con. Richmond.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Johannes Bell Archidiacon. Glouceſter.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Edmundus Bonner Archidia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con. Leiceſter.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Gulielmus Skippe Archidia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con. Dorſet.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Nicolaus Heth Archidiacon. Stafford.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Cuthbertus Marſhall Archidia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con. Nottingham.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Richardus Curten Archidia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con. Oxon.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Guilielmus Glife</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Galfridus Dounes</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Robertus Oking</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Radulphus Bradford</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Richardus Smith</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Simon Matthew</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Johannes P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>in</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Guilielmus Buckmaſter</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Guilielmus May</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Nicolaus Wotton</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Richardus Cox</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Johannes Edmunds</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Thomas Robertſon</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Johannes Baker</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Thomas Barret</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Johannes Haſe</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Johannes Tyſon.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>Theſe were Doctors of Divinity and both Laws.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="protestation">
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:200387:12"/>
            <head>A Proteſtation in the name of the King, and the whole Council and Clergy of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> why they refuſe to come to the Popes Council at his call.</head>
            <p>SEeing that the Biſhop of Rome calleth Learned Men from all parts, conducting them by great rewards,<note place="margin">The Kings Proteſtation why he ſends not to the Popes Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil.</note> making as many of them Cardinals as he thinketh moſt m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>et, and moſt ready to defend Frauds and Vntruths; we could not but with much anxiety caſt with our ſelves, what ſo great a preparance of Wits ſhould mean. As chance was we gueſſed even as it followed. We have been ſo long acquainted with Romiſh Subtilties and Popiſh Deceits,<note place="margin">The Popes craft eſpied.</note> that we well and eaſily judged the Biſhop of Rome to intend an Aſſembly of his Adherents, and men ſworn to think all his Luſts to be Laws; we were not deceived. <hi>Paul</hi> the Biſhop of Rome hath called a Council, to the which he knew well either few or none of the Chriſtian Princes could come; both the time that he indicted it, and alſo the place where he appointed it to be, might aſſure him of this. But whither wander not theſe Popiſh Bulls? whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther wander they not aſtray? What King is not cited and ſummoned by a proud Miniſter and Servant of Kings, to come to bolſter up Errors, Frauds, Deceits, and Vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truths, and to ſet forth this feigned General Council? For who will not think that <hi>Paul</hi> the Biſhop of Rome goeth ſooner about to make men believe that he pretendeth a Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Council, than that he deſireth one indeed? No, who can leſs deſire it, than they that do deſpair of their Cauſe, except they be Iudges and give ſentence themſelves againſt their Adverſaries?<note place="margin">The King not bound to come at the Popes call<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> We which very ſore againſt our will at any time leave off the procurement of the Realm any common weal, need neither to come our ſelves, nor yet to ſend any Procurators thither, no nor yet to make our Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe for either of both. For who can accuſe us that we come not at his call, which hath no Authority to call us?</p>
            <p>But for a ſeaſon let us (as a ſort of Blindlings do) grant that he may call us, and that he hath Authority ſo to do; yet (we pray you) may not all men ſee, what availeth it to come to this Council,<note place="margin">Who be they that have place in the Popes Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil.</note> where ye ſhall have no place except y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> be known both willing to oppreſs truth, and alſo ready t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> confirm and ſtabliſh Errors? Do not all men perceive <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> as we, with what integrity, fidelity, and religion,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:200387:13"/> theſe men go about to diſcuſs matters in controverſie, that take them in hand in ſo troubleſom a time as this is? Is it not plain what fruit the Commonweal of Chriſtendom may look for there,<note place="margin">The place of the Council not indiffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent.</note> whereas Mantua is choſen the place to keep his Council in? Is there any Prince not being of Italy, yea is there any of Italy, Prince or other diſſenting from the Pope, that dareth come to this Aſſembly and to this place? If there come none that dare ſpeak for trodden truth, none that will venture his life, is it mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel if the Biſhop of Rome being Iudge,<note place="margin">No reaſon that the Pope ſhould be Judge in his own cauſe.</note> no man repining, no man gainſaying, the Defenders of the Papacy obtain that Popiſh Authority, now quailling and almoſt faſten, to be ſet up again.</p>
            <p>Is this the way to help things afflict? to redreſs trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled Religion? to lift up oppreſſed truth? Shall men this way know whether the Roman Biſhops (which in very deed are,<note place="margin">The Biſhop of <hi>Rom</hi> in learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and life far under other Biſhops.</note> if ye look upon either their Doctrine or Life, far under other Biſhops) ought to be made like their Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows, that is, to be Paſtors in their own Dioceſe, and ſo to uſe no other power; or elſe whether they may make Laws, not onely unto other Biſhops, but alſo to Kings and Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours? O boldneſs, meet to be beaten down with force and not not to be convinced with Arguments. Can either <hi>Paul</hi> that now Lordeth, or any of his, earneſtly go about (if they alone, or at the leaſt without any Adverſary, be th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> in a corner aſſembled together) to heal the Sickneſſes, to take away the Errors, to pluck down the Abuſes that now are crept into the Church, and there be bolſtered up by ſuch Councils as now is like to be at Mantua?</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Paul</hi> the Pope proleth for his own pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit.</note>Is it very like that theſe, which prole for nothing but profit, will right gladly pull down all ſuch things as th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> Forefathers made, onely for the increaſe of Money? Wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> as their Forefathers, when their Honour, Power, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>macy was called into queſtion, would either in deſpigh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f Gods Law maintain their Dignity, or (to ſay better) their intolerable Pride? Is it like that theſe will not tread in their ſteps, and make naughty new Canons, whereby they may defend old evil Decrees? Howbeit, what need we to care either what they have done, or what they intend to do hereafter,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>England</hi> ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth her leave of the Pope for ever.</note> foraſmuch as England hath taken her leave of Popiſh Crafts for ever, never to be deluded with them here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after? Roman Biſhops have nothing to do with Engliſh People; the one doth not traffick with the other, at leaſt though they will have to do with us, yet we will none of their merchandiſe, none of their ſtuff, we will receive them of our council no more.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>England</hi> refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth the Popes Merchandiſe.</note> We have ſought our hurt, and bought our loſs a great while too long. Surely their De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees, either touching things ſet up or put down, ſhall have
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:200387:13"/> none other place with us than all Biſhops Decrees have, that is, if we like them we admit them, if we do not we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe them. But leſt peradventure men ſhall think us to follow our ſenſes too much, and that we moved by ſmall or no juſt cauſes, forſake the Authority, Cenſures, Decrees, and Popiſh Counſels, we thought it beſt here to ſhew our mind to the whole world. Wherefore we proteſt before God and all men, that we embrace, profeſs, and will ever ſo do, the right and holy Doctrine of Chriſt. All the Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles of his Faith, no jot omitted, be all ſo dear unto us, that we ſhould much ſooner ſtand in jeopardy of our Realm, than to ſee any point of Chriſts Religion in jeo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pardy with us.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>England</hi> goeth not from the unity of Faith although it goeth from the Pope.</note> We proteſt that we never went from the unity of his Faith, neither that we will depart an inch from it. No, we will much ſooner loſe our Lives, than any Article of our Belief ſhall decay in England. We, which in all this cauſe ſeek nothing but the glory of God, the profit and quietneſs of the World,<note place="margin">The Faith of <hi>England</hi> Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick. <hi>England</hi> ready to ſend to any General Council where truth may be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced.</note> proteſt that we can ſuffer Deceivers no longer. We never refuſed to come to a General Council; no, we promiſe all our labour, ſtudy, and fidelity, to the ſetting up of trodden Truth and trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled Religion in their place again, and to do all that ſhall lie in us to finiſh ſuch Controverſies as have a great while too long vexed Chriſtendom. Onely we will all Chriſtian men be admoniſhed, that we can ſuffer no longer that they be eſteemed willing to take away Errors, which indeed by all the ways their Wits will ſerve them go about this alone, that no man under pain of Death may ſpeak againſt any Error or Abuſe.</p>
            <p>We would have a Council, we deſire it, yea and crave no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſo oft of God as that we may have one. But yet we will that it be ſuch as Chriſtian men ought to have, that is, frank and free, where every man without fear may ſay his mind. We deſire that it be an holy Council,<note place="margin">What a true General Council ought to be.</note> where eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man may go about to ſet up Godlineſs, and not apply all their ſtudy to oppreſſing of Truth. We will it be Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, that is to ſay, kept at ſuch time and in ſuch place, that every man which ſeeketh the glory of God may be preſent, and there frankly utter his mind.<note place="margin">Conditions of a true Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Council.</note> For when it ſhall ſeem General, either when no man that diſſenteth from the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of Rome is compelled to be from it, or when they that be preſent are not letted by any juſt terror to ſay boldly what they truly think; for who would not gladly come to ſuch a Council, except it be the Pope, his Cardinals, and Popiſh Riſhops? On the other ſide, who is ſo fooliſh, whereas the chief point that is to be handled in this Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil is the Popes own Cauſe, Power, and Primacy, to grant that the Pope ſhould reign, ſhould be Iudge, ſhould be Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſident
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:200387:14"/> of the Council? If he which indeed can never think himſelf able to defend his Cauſe before any other Iudge,<note place="margin">The Pope would be Judge in his own cauſe.</note> be evermore made his own Iudge, and ſo Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſies not decided, but Errors ſet up, what can be deviſed in the Commonwealth of Chriſtendom more hurtful to the truth than General Councils?</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The Pope hath no pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to ſummon Councils.</note>And here to touch ſomewhat their impudent Arrogancy; By what Law, Power, or honeſt Title take they upon them to call Kings, to ſummon Princes to appear, where their Bulls command them? In time paſt all Councils were appointed by the Authority, Conſent, and Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Emperour, Kings, and Princes; why now ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth the Biſhop of Rome this upon him? Some will ſay, It is more likely that Biſhops will more tender the cauſe of Religion, gladlier have Errors taken away, than Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours, Kings, and Princes. The world hath good expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience of them, and every man ſeeth how faithfully they have handled religious matters. Is there any man that doth not ſee how vertuouſly <hi>Paul</hi> now goeth about by this occaſion to ſet up his Tyranny again?<note place="margin">The Pope how he can watch his time.</note> Is it not like that he that chooſeth ſuch a time as this is to keep a Council, much intendeth the redreſs of things that now are amiſs, that he ſeeketh the reſtoring of Religion, that now calleth a Council, the Emperour and the French King, two Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of great power, ſo bent to Wars that neither they, nor any other Chriſtian Prince can, in a manner do any thing but look for the end of this long War? Go too, go t o, Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of Rome, occaſion long wiſh'd for offereth her ſelf unto you; take her, ſhe openeth a Window for your Frauds to creep in at: call, your Cardinals, your own Creatures, ſhew them that this is a jolly time to deceive Princes in.</p>
            <p>O Fools! O wicked men! may we not juſtly ſo call you? Are ye not Fools, which being long ſuſpected not onely of Princes, but of all Chriſtian People in a manner, that in no caſe you could be brought to a General Council, plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſhew the whole world, that by theſe your Conciliables, your Hutter-mutter in corners, you take away all hope of lawful Catholick and General Council? Are you not wicked which ſo hate Truth,<note place="margin">Truth m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y be preſſed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed.</note> that except ſhe be utterly ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed ye will never ceaſe to vex her? The living God is alive, neither Truth his Dearling (he being alive) can be called to ſo great ſhame, contumely, and injury; or if it may be called to all theſe, yet can it come to none of them. Who is he that grievouſly lamenteth not men to be of ſuch ſhameful boldneſs,<note place="margin">The Pope Enemy to Chriſt.</note> to ſhew apertly that they be Enemies unto Chriſt himſelf? On the other ſide, who will not be glad to ſee ſuch men as fooliſh as they be wicked? The World is not now in a light ſuſpicion, as it hath been hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:200387:14"/> that you intend no reformation of Errors, but eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man ſeeth before his eyes your deceits, your wicked minds,<note place="margin">The Popes hatred againſt the truth.</note> your immortal hatred that ye bear againſt the Truth. Every man ſeeth how many miſerable Trage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies your pretence of an Vnity and Concord hath brought into Chriſtendom. They ſee your fair face of Peace hath ſerved Sedition, and troubled almoſt all Chriſtian Realms.<note place="margin">The Pope troubler of all Chriſtian Realms.</note> They ſee ye never oppugn Religion more, than when ye will ſeem moſt to defend it. They be ſorry to ſee that great Wits a long ſeaſon have ſpent their whole ſtrength in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of Deceits, Reaſon to put his whole power to the promoting of Pride and Vngodlineſs, Vertues to ſerve Vices, Holineſs to be ſlave to Hypocriſie, Prudence to Subtilty, Iuſtice to Tyranny. They be glad that Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture now fighteth for it ſelf, and not againſt it ſelf. They be glad that God is not compelled to be againſt God, Chriſt againſt Chriſt. They be glad that Subtilty hath done no more hurt to Religion in time paſt, than now Conſtancy doth do good to Truth.<note place="margin">The Popes marks where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at he ſhoot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth.</note> They ſee the Marks that ye have ſhot at in all your Councils paſt, to be Lucre, Money, Gains; they ſee you ſought your Profit, yea though it were joyn'd with the Slaughter of Truth. They ſee ye would ever that ſooner injury ſhould be done to the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, than that your Authority, that is to ſay, arrogant Impudency ſhould in any point be diminiſhed.</p>
            <p>And we pray you,<note place="margin">The Popes craft in ſteal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a General Council.</note> what may <hi>Paul</hi> the Biſhop of Rome ſeem now to go about, which ſeeing all Princes occupied in great affairs, would ſteal (as he calleth it) a General Council? What other thing, than hereby to have ſome excuſe to refuſe a General Council hereafter, when time and place much better for the handling of matters of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion ſhall be given unto Princes of Chriſtendom? He will think he may then do as Princes now do; he will think it lawful not to come then, becauſe Princes now come not. We pray God that we ever brawl not one with another in Religion; and whereas Diſſention is amongſt us, yet for our parts we do ſay, that we as much as men may, defend the better part, and be in the right way. We pray God that the world may enjoy peace and tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quillity, and that then we may have both time and place to ſettle Religion. For except firſt Princes agree, and ſo (War laid aſide) ſeek peace, he loſeth his labour that ſeeketh a General Council. If the Biſhop of Rome may keep his Council while they thus be together, will not there be made many pretty Decrees? If they which would come if they had leiſure be abſent, and we which (though we ſafely might come) will not loſe any part of our right, trow you in all our abſence that the Biſhop of Rome will not handle his Profit and Primacy well?</p>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:200387:15"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The time and pl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ce preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly picked of the Pope.</note>
               <hi>Paul,</hi> how can any of ours not refuſe to come to Mantua, through ſo many perils, a City ſo far ſet from England, ſo nigh your Friends, Kinſmen, and Adherents? Is he not unworthy of Life, that where he may tarry at home, will paſs through ſo many Ieopardies of Life? Can he which cometh to Cremona, a City not far from Mantua, be ſafe if he be taken not to be the Biſhop of Romes Friend,<note place="margin">What an He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retick is among the Papiſts.</note> that is, (as the common ſort of deceived people doth interpret) an Heretick? And if there come to Mantua ſuch a number as would furniſh a General Council, may not Mantua ſéem too little to receive ſo many Gueſts? Put theſe two toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, all the way from England to Mantua is full of juſt pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rils, and yet if ye eſcape all thoſe, the very place w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ere the Council is kept is more to be ſuſpected than all the way. Do ye not know all Civil Laws to compel no man to come to any place, where he ſhall be in jeopardy of his Life all the way? We have no ſafe conduct to paſs and return by the Dominions of other Princes. And if we had a ſafe conduct, yet ſhould not we be charged with raſhneſs, that where juſt terror might have diſſuaded us from ſuch a journey,<note place="margin">The way to <hi>Mantua</hi> long and danger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous.</note> we committed our ſelves to ſuch perils? Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly he that (the time being as it is, things ſtanding as they do) will go from England to Mantua, may be careleſs if he lack not wit; ſure of his arrival or return from thence he cannot be. For who doth not know how oft the Biſhops of Rome have plaid falſe parts with them that in ſuch matters have truſted to their ſafe conduct? How oft have they cauſed by their Perfidie ſuch men to be ſlain,<note place="margin">The falſhood of Popes no new thing.</note> as they have promiſed by their Faith before, that they ſhould both come ſafe and go ſafe? Theſe be no news, Popes to be falſe, Popes to keep no promiſe neither with God nor Man; Popes contrary to their oaths, to defile their cruel hands with honeſt mens bloud. But we tarry too long in things that as well touch all men as us.</p>
            <p>We will (theſe now laid apart) turn our Oration unto ſuch things, as privately touch both us King <hi>Henry</hi> the Eighth, and all Engliſhmen. Is it unknown to any man what mind <hi>Paul</hi> the Biſhop of Rome beareth to us King <hi>Henry</hi> the Eighth, to us his Nobility, to us his Graces Biſhops, and to us all his Graces Subjects<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> for the pulling down of his uſurped Power and proud Primacy, for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelling of his uſurped Iuriſdiction, and for delivering of our Realm from his grievous bondage and pollage? Who ſeeth not him even enflamed with hatred againſt us,<note place="margin">The hatred of the P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pe againſt <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi>
               </note> and the flames to be much greater than he can now keep them in? He is an open Enemy, he diſſembleth no longer, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voking all men by all the means that he can, to endamage us and our Country. Theſe three years he hath been oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupied
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:200387:15"/> in no one thing ſo much, as how he might ſtir up the Commons of England, and corrupting ſome with Money, ſome with Dignities. We let paſs what Letters he hath written to Chriſtian Princes; with how great fervent ſtudy he hath exhorted them to ſet upon us. The good Vicar of Chriſt by his doing ſheweth how he underſtands the words of Chriſt; he thinketh he playeth Chriſt's part well, when he may ſay as Chriſt did, <hi>Non veni pacem mittere in terram,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Pope bringeth not peace but the ſword to the earth, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe than Chriſt did.</note> 
               <hi>ſed gladium;</hi> I come not to make peace in earth, but to ſend ſwords about: and not ſuch ſwords as Chriſt would his to be armed withall, but ſuch as cruel Manquellers abuſe in the ſlaughter of their Neighbours. We marvel little though they vex'd other Princes oft, ſeeing they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence our favour ſhewed to them with contumelies, our benefits with injuries.</p>
            <p>We will not rehearſe here how many our Benefits be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed upon Roman Biſhops be loſt;<note place="margin">Benefits caſt away upon the Pope.</note> God be with ſuch ungrate Carles, unworthy to be numbered amongſt men; Certes ſuch that a man may well doubt whether God or Man hath better cauſe to hate them. But that we have learned to owe good will even to them that immortally hate us, what could we wiſh them ſo evil but they have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved much worſe? We wiſh them this hurt alone, that God ſend them a better mind. God be thanked we have made all their ſeditious intents ſooner to ſhew their great malice towards us, than to do us much hurt; yea, they have well taught us evermore to take good heed to our Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies. Vndoubtedly it were good going to Mantua, and to leave their Whelps among the Lambs of our Flock. When we be weary of our Wealth, we will even do then as they would have us now do. No, no, as long as we ſhall ſee his heart ſo good towards us, we truſt upon his warn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing we ſhall well provide to withſtand his cruel malice. No let him now ſpend his deceits, when they can hurt none but ſuch as would deceive and are deceived.</p>
            <p>They have by ſundry ways made us privy how much we be bound to them. It went nigh their hearts to ſee the judgment of <hi>July,</hi> of <hi>Clement</hi> the ſeventh, of <hi>Paul</hi> the third, nothing to be regarded with us. They be afraid if we ſhould ſuſtain no hurt, becauſe we juſtly rejected their Primacy, that other Princes would begin to do likewiſe,<note place="margin">The Popes Curſes not feared in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi>
               </note> and to ſhake from their ſhoulders the heavy burthens that they ſo long have born, againſt Scripture, all right and reaſon. They be ſorry to ſee the way ſtopped, that now their Tyranny, Avarice, and Pride can have no paſſage into England, which was wont to walk, to triumph, to toſs; to trouble all men. They can ſcarce ſuffer Privile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, that is to ſay, Licence to ſpoil our Citizens, given
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:200387:16"/> them by our Forefathers, and brought in by errorfull Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom, to be taken from them. They think it unlawful, that we require things lawful of them that will be under no Laws. They think we do them wrong becauſe we will not ſuffer them to do us wrong any longer. They ſee their Merchandize to be baniſhed,<note place="margin">The Popes Trumpery diſpa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ned out of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi>
               </note> to be forbidden; they ſee that we will buy no longer Chalk for Cheeſe. They ſee that they have loſt a fair fleece, vengeable ſorry that they can diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patch no more Pardons, Diſpenſations, Totquots, with the reſt of their baggage and trumpery. England is no more a Babe; there is no man here but now he knoweth that they do fooliſhly that give Gold for Lead,<note place="margin">Gold given for Lead.</note> more weight of that than they receive of this; they paſs not, though <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Pauls</hi> Faces be graven in the Lead to make Fools fain. No, we be ſorry that they ſhould abuſe holy Saints Viſages to the beguiling of the world.</p>
            <p>Surely, except God take away our right wits, not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly his Authority ſhall be driven out for ever, but his Name alſo ſhall be forgotten in England.<note place="margin">God grant.</note> We will from henceforth ask counſel from him and his when we liſt to be deceived, when we covet to be in error, when we deſire to offend God, Truth and Honeſty. If a man may gueſs the whole work by the foundation,<note place="margin">The Popes foundation to all deceits.</note> where Deceits begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth the work, can any other than Deceits be builded up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this foundation? What can you look for in this Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuan Council, other than the oppreſſion of Truth and true Religion? If there be any thing well done, think as eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man doth, Biſhops of Rome to be accuſtomed to do a few things well, that many evil may the better be taken at their hands.<note place="margin">The Pope doth a few things well, that many evils may the bet er pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed.</note> They when they liſt can yield ſome part of their right; they are content that ſome of their Decrees, ſome of their Errors and Abuſes be reprehended, but they are never more to be feared than when they ſhew them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves moſt gentle. For if they grant a few they ask ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, if they leave a little they will be ſure of a great deal. Scarce a man may know how to handle himſelf, that he take no hurt at their hands, yea when they bleſs him; which ſeldom do good but for an intent to do evil. Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly, come who ſo will to theſe Shops of Deceits, to theſe Fairs of Frauds, we will loſe no part of our right in coming at his call,<note place="margin">The Pope ought to be called, and not to call.</note> that ought to be called and not to call. We will neither come at Mantua, nor ſend thither for this matter, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>And ſo the King proceeding in the ſaid his Proteſtation declareth moreover, how the Pope after he had ſummoned his Council firſt to be kept at Mantua,<note place="margin">The Pope again pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es his Council.</note> the three and twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tieth day of May, An. 1537, ſhortly after directed out ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Bull to prorogate the ſame Council to the moneth of
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:200387:16"/> November, pretending for his excuſe that the Duke of Mantua would not ſuffer him to keep any Council there, unleſs he maintained a number of Warriours for defence of the Town. And therefore in his later Bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l he proro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gueth this Aſſembly, commanding Patriarchs, Archbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, Biſhos, Abbats, and other of the Spiritualty, by the vertue of Obedience, and under pain of Curſing, to be preſent, but ſheweth no place at all where he would be, nor whither they ſhould come. And in very deed no great matter though no place were named; for as good a Council no where to be called, as where it could not be; and as well no place ſerved him that intended no Council, as all places. And to ſay truth, much better no place to be na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, than to name ſuch as he purpoſed not to come to; for ſo ſhould he break no promiſe which maketh none. And ſo going forward in his Oration, toward the later end he thus inferreth by his words of Proteſtation, ſaying:</p>
            <p>No,<note place="margin">Princes as the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> gave the Pope Prima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, ſo they take it from him again.</note> we will the Pope and his Adherents to underſtand that which we have oft ſaid, and now ſay, and ever will ſay, He nor his hath no Authority nor Iuriſdiction in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land; we give him no more than he hath, that is never a deal. That which he hath uſurped againſt Gods Law, and extorteth by violence, we by good right take from him again. But he and his will ſay, we gave them a Prima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy. We bear them well, we gave it you indeed; if you have Authority upon us as long as our Conſent giveth it you, and you evermore will make your plea upon our Conſent, then let it have even an end where it began; we conſent no longer, your Authority muſt needs be gone. If we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing deceived by falſe pretence of evil-alledged Scriptures, gave to you that ye ought to have refuſed, why may we not, our Error now perceived, and your Deceit eſpied, take it again? We Princes wrote our ſelves to be inferiour to Popes; as long as we thought ſo we obeyed them as our Superiours. Now we write not as we did, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they have no great cauſe to marvel, if we hereafter do not as we did; both the Laws Civil, and alſo the Laws of God, be on our ſide. For a Fraeman born doth not loſe his Liberty, no nor hurt the plea of his Liberty, though he write himſelf a Bondman.</p>
            <p>Again, if they lean to Cuſtom,<note place="margin">Cuſtom.</note> we ſend them to S. <hi>Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prian,</hi> which ſaith, That Cuſtom, if Truth be not joyned with it, is nothing but <hi>Erroris vetuſtas,</hi> that is, an old Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror. Chriſt ſaid, <hi>Ego ſum via, veritas, &amp; vita;</hi> I am the way, the truth, and the life: he never ſaid, <hi>Ego ſum con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuetudo,</hi> I am the Cuſtom. Wherefore ſeeing Cuſtom ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth you on the one ſide, and Scripture us on the other, are ye able to match us? In how many places doth
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:200387:17"/> Chriſt moniſh you to ſeek no Primacy, to prefer your ſelves before nobody, no to be obedient unto all Creatures? Your old Title <hi>Servus Servorum</hi> evil agreeth your new forged Dignity.<note place="margin">The Popes Title and his Dignity agree not together.</note> But we will not tarry in matters ſo plain; we onely deſire God, that <hi>Caeſar,</hi> and other Chriſtian Princes, would agree upon ſome holy Council, where truth may be tried, and Religion ſet up, which hath been hurt by no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſo ſore, as by general not General Councils. Errors and Abuſes grow too faſt; <hi>Erudimini qui judicatis terram,</hi> Get you Learning you that judge the earth; and excogi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate ſome Remedy for theſe ſo many Diſeaſes of the ſick Church. They that be wiſeſt do deſpair of a General Council;<note place="margin">Beſt that eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Prince re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form his own Realm, and tarry not for General Councils.</note> wherefore we think it now beſt that every Prince call a Council Provincial, and every Prince to redreſs his own Realm. We make all men privy what we think beſt to be done for the redreſs of Religion: if they like it, we doubt not but they will follow it, or ſome other better. Our truſt is, that all Princes will ſo handle themſelves in this behalf, that Princes may enjoy their own, and Prieſts of Rome content themſelves with that they ought to have. Princes as we truſt will no longer nouriſh Wolves Whelps, they will ſubſcribe no more to Popiſh Pride, to the Papacy, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Favour our doings, O Chriſtian Princes, your Honour and ancient Majeſty is reſtored. Remember there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing peetaining ſo much to a Princes Honour, as to ſet forth Truth, and to help Religion. Take you heed that their Deceits work not more miſchief than your Vertue can do good, and everlaſting War we would all Princes had with this Papacy. As for their Decrees, ſo hearken to them, that if in this Mantuan Aſſembly things be well done ye take them, but not as authorized by them, but that Truth, and things that maintain Religion, are to be taken at all mens hands. And even as we will admit things well made, ſo if there be any thing determined in prejudice of Truth, for the maintainance of their evil grounded Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy, or that may hurt the Authority of Kings, we proteſt unto the whole world, that we neither allow it, nor will at any time allow it.</p>
            <p>Ye have, Chriſtian Readers, our mind concerning the General Council; we think you all ſee that <hi>Paul</hi> and his Cardinals, Biſhops, Abbats, Monks, Friers, with the reſt of the Rabblement, do nothing leſs intend, than the Knowledge of Truth. Ye ſee this is no time meet, Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tua no place meet for a General Council; and though they were both meet, yet except ſome other call this Council, you ſee that we neither need to come nor to ſend. You have heard how every Prince in his own Realm may quiet
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:200387:17"/> things amiſs. If there be any of you that can ſhew us a better way, we promiſe with all our hearty deſire to do that that ſhall be thought beſt for the ſettling of Religion, and that we will leave our own Advices if any man ſhew us better. Which mind of ours we moſt heartily pray God that gave it us, not onely to increaſe in us, but alſo to ſend it unto all Chriſtian Princes, all Chriſtian Prelats, and all Chriſtian People.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="injunctions">
            <head>Injunctions given by King <hi>Henry</hi> VIII. to the Clergy of his Realm.</head>
            <p>IN the Name of God, Amen. In the Year of our Lord God 1536, and of the moſt Noble Reign of our Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Lord <hi>Henry VIII.</hi> King of England and of France, Defender of the Faith, Lord of Ireland, and in the earth Supreme Head of the Church of England, the twenty eighth, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>I <hi>Thomas Cromwell</hi> Knight, Lord <hi>Cromwell,</hi> Keeper of the Privy Seal of our ſaid Sovereign Lord the King, and Vicegerent to the ſame; for and concerning all his Iuriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction Eccleſiaſtical within this Realm, to the glory of Almighty God, to the Kings Highneſs Honour, the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick weal of this Realm, and increaſe of Vertue in the ſame, have appointed and aſſigned theſe Injunctions en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuing, to be kept and obſerved of the Dean, Parſons, Vicars, Curats, and Stipendaries, reſident or having Cure of Souls, or any other Spiritual Adminiſtration within this Deanry, under the Pains hereafter limited and appointed.</p>
            <p>THE firſt is, that the Dean, Parſons, Vicars, and other having Cure of Souls any where within this Deanry, ſhall faithfully keep and obſerve, and as far as in them may lie, ſhall cauſe to be kept and obſerved of all other, all and ſingular Laws and Statutes of this Realm, made for the aboliſhing and extirpation of the Biſhop of Romes pretended and uſurped Power and Iuriſdiction within this Realm,<note place="margin">Confirmation of the Kings Supremacy.</note> and for the eſtabliſhment and confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of the Kings Authority and Iuriſdiction within the ſame, as of the Supreme Head of the Church of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, and ſhall to the uttermoſt of their Wit, Knowledge,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:200387:18"/> and Learning, purely, ſyncerely, and without any colour or diſſimulation, declare, manifeſt, and open, by the ſpace of one quarter of a year now next enſuing, once every Sunday, and after at the leaſt twice every quarter of a year, in their Sermons and other Collations, that the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of Romes Vſurped Power and Iuriſdiction,<note place="margin">Againſt the Popes Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy.</note> having no eſtabliſhment nor ground by the Law of God, was for moſt juſt cauſes taken away and a boliſhed, and that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they owe unto him no manner of Obedience or Subje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and that the Kings Power is within his Dominion the higheſt Potentate and Power under God, to whom all men within the ſame Dominion, by Gods, commandment owe moſt Loyalty and Obedience, afore and above all other Potentates in earth.</p>
            <p>Item, Whereas certain Articles were lately deviſed and put forth by the Kings Highneſs Authority, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſcended unto by the Prelats and Clergy of this his Realm in Convocation, (whereof part were neceſſary to be holden and believed for our Salvation, and the other part do concern and touch certain laudable Ceremonies, Rights, and Vſages of the Church, meet and convenient to be kept and uſed for a decent and politick order in the ſame) the ſaid Dean, Parſons, Vicars, and other Curats, ſhall ſo open and declare, in their Sermons and other Collati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, the ſaid Articles unto them that be under their Cure, that they may plainly know and diſcern which of them be neceſſary to be believed and obſerved for their Salvation, and which be not neceſſary, but onely do concern the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent and politick order of the ſaid Church, according to ſuch commandment and admonition as hath been given unto them heretofore by the Authority of the Kings High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in that behalf.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The Kings Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles to be read to the people.</note>Moreover, that they ſhall declare unto all ſuch as be under their Cure, the Articles likewiſe deviſed, put forth, and authorized of late, for and concerning the abrogating of certain ſuperſtitious Holydays, according to the effect and purport of the ſame Articles, and perſuade their Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhioners to keep and obſerve the ſame inviolably, as things wholſom, provided, decreed, and eſtabliſhed by the common Conſent and publick Authority, for the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weals commodity and profit of all this Realm.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Images abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed.</note>Beſides this, to the intent that all Superſtition and Hypocriſie crept into divers mens hearts may vaniſh away, they ſhall not ſet forth or extoll any Images, Reliques, or Miracles, for any ſuperſtition or lucre, nor allure the peo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:200387:18"/> by any intreatments to Pilgrimages<note place="margin">Pilgrimages Forbidden.</note> of any Saints, otherwiſe than is permitted in the Articles lately put forth by the Authority of the Kings Majeſty, and conde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcended unto by the Prelats and Clergy of this his Realm in Convocation, as though it were proper or peculiar to that Saint to give this Commodity or that; ſeeing all Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Health, and Grace, ought to be both looked and ask<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for onely of God, as of the very Author of the ſame, and of none other, for without him it cannot be given; but they ſhall exhort as well their Pariſhioners as other Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grims, that they do rather apply themſelves to the keeping of Gods Commandments, and the fulfilling of his works of Charity; perſuading them that they ſhall pleaſe God more by the true exerciſe of their bodily Labour, Travel, or Occupation, and providing for their Families, than if they went about to the ſaid Pilgrimages; and it ſhall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit more their Souls health, if they do beſtow that on the poor and needy, which they would have beſtowed upon the ſaid Images or Reliques.</p>
            <p>Alſo in the ſame their Sermons and other Collations,<note place="margin">Prayers in the Mother Tongue.</note> the Parſons, Vicars, and other Curats aforeſaid, ſhall di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligently admoniſh the Fathers and Mothers, Maſters and Governours of Youth, being within their Cure, to teach or cauſe to be taught their Children and Servants, even from their Infancy, the <hi>Pater noſter,</hi> the Articles of our Faith, and the Ten Commandments in their Mother Tongue, and the ſame ſo taught ſhall cauſe the ſaid Youth oft to repeat and underſtand. And to the intent this may be the more eaſily done, the ſaid Curats ſhall in their Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons deliberately and plainly recite of the ſaid <hi>Pater no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter,</hi> Articles, or Commandments, one Clauſe or Article one day, and another another day, till the whole be taught and learned by little and little, and ſhall deliver the ſame in writing, or ſhew where printed Books containing the ſame be to be ſold to them that can read, or will deſire the ſame; and thereto that the ſaid Fathers and Mothers, Maſters and Governours, do beſtow their Children and Servants, even from their Childhood, either to Learning or to ſome honeſt Exerciſe, Occupation, or Husbandry; ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horting, counſelling, and by all the ways and means they may, as well in their ſaid Sermons and Collations, as otherwiſe, the ſaid Fathers, Mothers, Maſters, and other Governours, being under their cure and charge, diligently to provide and foreſee,<note place="margin">For bringing up of Youth in ſome Art or Occupati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> that the ſaid Youth be in no manner wiſe kept or brought up in idleneſs, leſt at any time after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward they be driven, for lack of ſome Myſtery or Occupa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to live by, to fall to begging, ſtealing, or ſome other
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:200387:19"/> unthriftineſs; foraſmuch as we may daily ſee, through ſloth and idleneſs divers valiant men fall, ſome to begging, ſome to theft and murther, which after brought to calami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and miſery, impute a great part thereof to their Friends and Governours, which ſuffered them to be brought up ſo idly in their Youth; where if they had been brought up and educated in ſome good Literature, Occupation or Myſtery, they ſhould (being Rulers of their own Families) have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fited as well themſelves as divers other perſons, to the great commodity and ornament of the Commonweal.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Placing of good Vicars and Curats.</note>Alſo that the ſaid Parſons, Vicars, and other Curats, ſhall diligently provide, that the Sacraments and Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentals be duly and reverently miniſtred in their Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhes. And if at any time it happen them, either in any of the caſes expreſſed in the Statutes of this Realm, or of ſpecial Licence given by the Kings Majeſty, to be abſent from their Benefices, they ſhall leave their Cure not to a rude and unlearned perſon, but to an honeſt, well learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and expert Curat, that may teach the rude and unlearn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of their Cure wholſom Doctrine, and reduce them to the right way, that they do not erre; and always let them ſee, that neither they nor their Vicars do ſeek more their own profit, promotion, or advantage, than the profit of the Souls that they have under their Cure, or the glory of God.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Every Pariſh to provide a Bible in Engliſh.</note>Item, that every Parſon or Proprietary of any Pariſh Church within this Realm, ſhall on this ſide the Feaſt of S. <hi>Peter ad vincula</hi> next coming, provide a Book of the whole Bible both in Latin and alſo in Engliſh, and lay the ſame in the Quire, for every man that will to look and read thereon, and ſhall diſcourage no man from the read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of any part of the Bible, either in Latin or Engliſh, but rather to comfort, exhort, and moniſh every man to read the ſame as the very Word of God, and the ſpiritual food of mans Soul, whereby they may the better know their Duties to God, to their Sovereign Lord the King, and their Neighbour; ever gently and charitably ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horting them, that uſing a ſober and modeſt behaviour in the reading and inquiſition of the true ſenſe of the ſame, they do in no wiſe ſtiffly or eagerly contend or ſtrive one with another about the ſame, but refer the declaration of thoſe places that be in controverſie, to the judgment of them that be better learned.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Prieſts not to haunt Ale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſes.</note>Alſo the ſaid Dean, Parſons, Vicars, Curats, and other Prieſts, ſhall in no wiſe at any unlawful time, nor for
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:200387:19"/> any other cauſe than for their honeſt neceſſity, haunt or reſort to any Taverns or Alehouſes, and after their Din<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner and Supper they ſhall not give themſelves to drinking or riot, ſpending their time idly by day or by night, at Tables or Cards playing, or any other unlawful Game; but at ſuch times as they ſhall have ſuch leiſure, they ſhall read or hear ſomewhat of holy Scripture, or ſhall occupy themſelves with ſome honeſt Exerciſe, and that they al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways do thoſe things that appertain to good congruence and honeſty, with profit of the Commonweal, having al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways in mind that they ought to excell all other in purity of life, and ſhould be example to all other to live well and Chriſtianly.</p>
            <p>Furthermore,<note place="margin">Parſons not reſident to pay the 40th. part to their Pariſhes.</note> becauſe the goods of the Church are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the goods of the Poor, and in theſe days nothing is leſs ſeen than the Poor to be ſuſtained with the ſame, all Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, Vicars, Prebendaries, and other beneficed men with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in this Deanry, not being reſident upon their Benefices, which may diſpend yearly twenty pounds or above, either within this Deanry, or elſewhere, ſhall diſtribute hereafter yearly amongſt their poor Pariſhioners or other Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants there, in the preſence of the Churchwardens, or ſome other honeſt men of the Pariſh, the fortieth part of the Fruits and Revenues of their ſaid Benefices, leſt they be worthily noted of Ingratitude, which reſerving ſo many parts to themſelves, cannot vouchſafe to impart the forti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth portion thereof amongſt the poor people of that Pariſh that is ſo fruitful and profitable unto them.</p>
            <p>And to the intent that learned men may hereafter ſpring the more, for the executing of the ſaid premiſſes,<note place="margin">Every bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficed man worth 100 <hi>l.</hi> to find a Scho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar at the Univerſity.</note> every Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, Vicar, Clerk, or beneficed man within this Deanry, yearly to ſpend in Benefices or other Promotions of the Church, an hundred pounds, ſhall give competent Exhibiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to one Scholar; and for as many hundred pounds more as he may diſpend, to ſo many Scholars more ſhall give like Exhibition in the Vniverſity of Oxford or Cambridge, or ſome Grammar School; which after they have profited in good Learning, may be Partners of their Patrons Cure and Charge, as well in Preaching, as otherwiſe in the execution of their Offices, or may when need ſhall be other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe profit the Commonwealth with their counſel and wiſdom.</p>
            <p>Alſo that all Parſons, Vicars, and Clerks,<note place="margin">Beneficed men to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain their Manſions.</note> having Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, Chapels, or Manſions within this Deanry, ſhall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow yearly hereafter upon the ſame Manſions or Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:200387:20"/> of their Churches being in decay, the fifth part of thoſe their Benefices, till they ſhall be fully repaired, and the ſame ſo repaired they ſhall always keep and maintain in good eſtate.</p>
            <p>All which and ſingular Injunctions ſhall be inviolably obſerved of the ſaid Dean, Parſons, Vicars, Curats, Sti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendaries, and other Clerks, and beneficed men under pain of Suſpenſion, and Sequeſtration of the Fruits of their Benefices, untill they have done their duties accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to theſe Injunctions.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:200387:20"/>
            <head>Poſtſcript.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>CHriſtian Reader,</hi> Who haſt peruſed and well weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed this Proteſtation, thou doſt ſee therein the Frauds, Pride, Avarice, Treacheries, Cruelties, Enmity to God and Chriſt, and his Truth and People, with many other notorious Enormities of the Pope and his Shaveling Prieſts and Clergy, clearly and openly diſcovered, detected, deteſted and renounced, by ſo great a King. He pronounces them to be open Enemies to Chriſt himſelf, and to carry in their Breaſts an immortal Hatred to his Truth. He Proclaimeth to all Chriſtian Princes and Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble the miſerable Tragedies, which under pretence of Unity and Concord, they have brought into <hi>Chriſtendom,</hi> and that they have troubled all Chriſtian Realms with Seditions, under plauſible pretences of Peace. That in all their Councils and Actings touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Religion, the only Marks they have ſhot at, was Lucre, Money and Gains; yea that they ſought their own Profit, with the Slaughter of the Truth, and were infinitely more willing that the greateſt Injury ſhould be done to the Goſpel, than that their Authority, that is to ſay, their Arrogant Impudence, ſhould ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer the leaſt Diminution. That their uſual practice is, to defile their cruel Hands with honeſt Mens Bloud, and that contrary to their Oaths. He further declares, That this holy Vicar was ſo inflamed with Hatred againſt the King and Kingdom, for pull<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing down his Uſurped Power, and Proud Primacy, for expelling his Uſurped Juriſdiction, for rejecting his Falſe and Heretical Doctrine, and delivering this Realm from his grievous Bondage and Polage; that <hi>He</hi> ſought by all ways to endamage both King and People; and by Enemies at <hi>Home</hi> and Princes <hi>Abroad,</hi> to ſtir up Troubles and Commotions. Upon which ſufficient Grounds, and for which juſt Cauſes, he thus reſolves, ſaying, <hi>Surely ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept God take away our right Wits, not only his Authority,</hi> to wit the Popes, <hi>ſhall be driven out for</hi> Ever, <hi>but his Name alſo ſhall ſhortly be forgotten in</hi> England. And again, <hi>We will ha' the Pope and his Adherents to underſtand that which we have oft ſaid, and now ſay, and ever will ſay, He nor His hath no Authority or Juriſdiction in</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land. <hi>That which he hath uſurped againſt Gods Law, and extorted by Violence, We by good right take from him again.</hi> And <hi>He</hi> exhorts all Chriſtian Princes to favour and follow his Godly and Juſt Proceedings.</p>
            <p>Thus did God of his Infinite Goodneſs raiſe up this Great and Wiſe King to root out the Pope's Uſurped Authority, and Falſe Religion alſo, in a great meaſure, out of <hi>England;</hi> and the Lord grant that theſe Intolerable and Unſupportable Evils may be kept
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:200387:21"/> out of it for ever. For without doubt, that Curſe of God which <hi>Joſhua</hi> pronounced againſt him that ſhould <hi>Rebuild Jericho,</hi> which was deſtroyed by the Word and Power of God, according as it is written, <hi>Joſhua</hi> 6.26. <hi>And</hi> Joſhua <hi>adjured them at that time, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Curſed be the Man before the Lord that riſeth up and Buildeth this City</hi> Jericho, which was accordingly fulfiled in <hi>Hiel</hi> the <hi>Bethelite</hi> in the days of <hi>Ahab.</hi> I am very well aſſured, that that, and a greater Curſe will be the Portion of that Man from the Lord, that ſhall riſe up and Rebuild this Spiritual <hi>Babylon</hi> again in <hi>England,</hi> to wit, the <hi>Antichriſtian</hi> Church, which the Word and Power of God hath deſtroyed, and now for ſeveral happy Years kept out of this Nation. <hi>Et nunc Reges intelligite, erudimini qui Judicatis terram. Be wiſe now therefore O Ye Kings, be inſtructed Ye that judge the Earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And Oh ye People, be not as the Horſe and Mule that have no Underſtanding, but as Men at leaſt, and (if it may be) as Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans: conſider and weigh well with your ſelves the great and inex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicable Evils that the poor Nation now groans under, none can tell for how long; ſome of which are theſe that follow, and grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter cannot be told.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Suppreſſing the Glorious Light of the Goſpel, and Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing it out of Publique View; the ſilencing the Grace of Chriſts own Lips, and cauſing the Joyful Sound that Proclaims the Acceptable Year of the Lord, to ceaſe out of our Borders. And this is the Evil of Evils, and the Miſery of Miſeries which brings all other Evils and Miſeries along with it; yea this ſhuts up the Kingdom of Heaven from the World, and ſets Hell wide open, for all men to run headlong into it, as we ſee it done this day. This excludes the Love, Mercy and Goodneſs of God from the World, as much as poſſibly it can, and brings in his Wrath and heavy Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure to waſt and conſume it; of which we have had the ſad and moſt exquiſite Experience, now alas! for ſeveral years toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. For ſince the Goſpel, under ſeveral Mulcts and Penalties, hath been forbidden to be Preach'd, how many Manifeſtations of Gods Juſt Anger have we ſeen in many ſtrange and unuſual Prodigies, in the Heavens, in the Earth, in the Waters, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing loud Warnings of the Wrath to come. What a grievous and deſolating Plague, the Scourge of the Almighty, hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed Thouſands and Ten Thouſands in that late great C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> and in many other parts of the Nation, the like whereunto hath not been heretofore? What a dreadful Conflagration hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured that Famous and Incomparable City, the Head and Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of theſe Nations, and laid it in Aſhes and Ruines like <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Gomorrah?</hi> which Cities were ſet on Fire from Heaven, but this from Hell, by the Locuſts of the Bottomleſs Pit, the Emiſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of the Pope and his Clergy, which Vermin have ſwarmed in this Nation, ſince the removal of the Goſpel.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:200387:21"/>
            <p>And this provoking Sin, is not ſo much the Sin of the People, as of the Powers of the Nation, who as it were, of very Malice, have openly renounced <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and deſired <hi>Barabbas</hi> to be given to them in his ſtead; they have rejected the Sweet and Meek Goſpel of Chriſt, and have deſired to be given to then the Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el and Murderous Religion of <hi>Antichriſt;</hi> a Religion written in Red Letters, even in Letters of Bloud; for it hath ſhed the bloud of innumerable Saints and Martyrs in the ſeveral Ages, ſince An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt firſt lift up his Head out of Hell into this World; ſeduce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Powers of the World to take part with him in this blou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy Work. This Religion, or rather this Iniquity in the Suburbs of it, we ſee Erected already, and now the great City thereof, is ready to be built again; and this Kingdom of Darkneſs could never have been founded but in the abſence of the Light, which they have violently chaſed away. And this one thing carrys weight in it, that they who tolerate <hi>Popery</hi> to take its eaſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong us, and to lengthen its Cords, and to ſtrengthen its Stakes, though it be directly againſt Chriſt; and they who tolerate the open exerciſe of the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Religion, which denies and blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemes Chriſt, will by no means ſuffer nor endure the true and ſincere Goſpel of Chriſts Kingdom to be publiſhed by any, but un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der great Penalties. Whereby they declare, that they are of one Council and Work with Satan, who hath with all his Subtilty and Cruelty fought againſt Chriſt and his Goſpel, from the firſt day of their Heavenly Birth hitherto.</p>
            <p>This is the firſt and greateſt Evil the Nation mourns and groans under, but this is not all.</p>
            <p>For <hi>Secondly,</hi> From hence follows the greateſt and deepeſt ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance of God and Chriſt that can be, and of all their unſearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Riches which the Goſpel hath diſcovered to the World. The greateſt ignorance of the Law and of the Goſpel, of Sin and of Righteouſneſs, of Salvation and Damnation, of Heaven and Hell; in a word, the groſſeſt ignorance of all the Revealed Truths of God, which concern us either to obtain Eternal Life, or to avoid Endleſs Death. So that in <hi>India</hi> and <hi>Ethiopia,</hi> in <hi>Calno</hi> and <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chemiſh,</hi> in <hi>Pathros</hi> and <hi>Cuſh,</hi> in <hi>Meſech</hi> and the Tents of <hi>Kedar,</hi> there is not greater ignorance of Chriſt and his Goſpel, and of the way of Salvation, to be found than in many places, and among many People in <hi>England;</hi> the true report that may be given of it is even incredible. And would it not grievouſly affect any Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Mans heart to behold ſo many thouſands of Children in this Nation, brought up without any right inſtruction in the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Religion? Oh conſider, what a Profane and Heatheniſh Nation this muſt neceſſarily become in a few years! for, what the Children and Youths now are, the Common-Wealth will be in twenty or thirty Years. And what a bruitiſh and beaſt-like Generation will then People be in this Land, if the Lord take not care of this matter in the mean time. When few will be found
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:200387:22"/> who ſhall know any more of Chriſts Name than what thay capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citate them to blaſpheme it, or of his moſt Precious Death and Crucifying, more than to ſerve them to Swear by his Bloud and Wounds. For the glorious Sun of Divine Knowledge, is three quarters Eclipſed already: the Good Lord prevent the Total Eclipſe thereof, by ſending forth again Miniſters of his own chooſing and anointing, to feed his People with true Knowledge and Underſtanding.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> The third Miſery we ſigh under, is the overflowing of Iniquity like the mighty Waves of the Sea. Never was there ſuch a Deluge of Sin ſeen upon Earth, as now covers the Face of the Nation; this is even become the covering of all Fleſh. All ſorts of People, of High and Low Degree, whether Secular or Eceleſiaſtical, are all drencht and dyed in it; in ſuch ſort, that Men live in this World in the manifeſt likeneſs of the Devil, and if Satan himſelf were Incarnate, you could not eaſily diſcern one from the other. They ſet their Faces againſt Heaven, and call out upon God to Damn them, Soul and Body. So Diveliſh they are, that they would fain be tormented before their time, and do oft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en provoke Hell to ſwallow them up; for becauſe they can be no liker to the Devil in this World, they would haſten to Hell that there they may be fully like him. Oh Monſters of Mankind! Oh the true Seed of the Serpent! the right <hi>Generation of Vipers!</hi> Ye have been fore-warn'd by God to flee from the Wrath to come, but who hath warn'd you to flee unto it? Who among the remote Nations would believe the report of all your Villanies? The very rehearſal of them would put them into Pangs, and the bare hearing of them into Tremblings: their Sayings and Doings are ſuch, as are not fit to be mentioned or recited among Men, but onely in the midſt of Devils. For who without horrible fear, could either repeat or hear their deſperate Blaſphemies againſt God himſelf, glorious in Holineſs, and againſt our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, (whom God hath made his Firſt-Bor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>High<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r than the Kings of the Earth;</hi> and <hi>when he brought him into the World, he ſaid, Let all the Angels Worſhip Him</hi>) and againſt the Holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit (againſt whom <hi>whoever ſpeaks a word, it ſhall nev<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r be forgiven him</hi>) againſt the bleſſed Goſpel the great and onely <hi>Power of God to Salvation</hi>) againſt the Kingdom of God on Earth, and againſt them that dwell in Heaven. Therefore, O Lord, forgive them not.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>For their Vine is as the Vine of</hi> Sodom, <hi>and of the Fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lds of</hi> Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morrah, <hi>their Grapes are Grapes of Gall, their Cluſters are bitter, their Wine is the Poyſon of Dragons, and the cruel Venome of Aſps. The ſhew of their Countenance doth witneſs againſt them, and they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare their Sin more than</hi> Sodom, <hi>they hide it not, they boaſt of it, and every Man is famous as he can do most wickedly. Wo unto their Souls, for they have rewarded evil againſt themſelves.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:200387:22"/>
            <p>
               <hi>For therefore H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll hath enlarged her ſelf, and opened her Mouth without meaſure, and their Glory, and their Multitude, and their Pomp, and he that rejoiceth ſhall ſoon deſcend into it. This their Day approacheth, it comes, it makes haſt, when they ſhall periſh for ever like their own Dung, and they that have ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>en them ſhall ſay, where are they?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And therefore howl ye Profane Ones, for the Day of the Lord is at hand, it ſhall come as a Deſtruction from the Almighty: then ſhall your Wicked Hands fall down, and your Proud Hearts melt, and you ſhall be ſorely afraid; Pangs and Sorrow ſhall take hold on you, even Pangs as of a Woman in Travel: and when ye ſhall look to one another ye ſhall he amazed at one another, and your faces ſhall alter and change colour as Flames. For b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hold the Day of the Lord cometh cruel, both with Wrath and fierce Anger, to lay the Land deſolate for your ſakes, and he ſhall deſtroy the Sinn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rs thereof out of it. And he will puniſh the World for th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ir evil, and the Wicked for their wick<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dneſs, he will make the Arrogancy of the Proud Ones to c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aſe, and will lay low the Haughtineſs of the Terrible Ones. In that day</hi> Sodom <hi>and</hi> Gomor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rah <hi>ſhall riſe up in Judgment againſt you, and it ſhall be more tolerable for them than for you,</hi> O Ye Profane Ones of <hi>England!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe Spiritual Evils preſs us ſore; As for our Outward Evils, they are well known and felt by All, of all ſorts; and though I ſhould be ſilent in the rehearſing them, they ſpeak forth them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. They are a ſore not to be touched; yet if no hand ſhould touch them, how ſhould they he healed? Wherefore I will in the Name and Fear of God make mention of one of them, and of ſuch an one as briefly compreheds all the reſt.</p>
            <p>And this is, The ſtrange and diſmal Withering, Waſting, Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhing and Dying Condition of Poor <hi>England,</hi> whoſe common Welfare no Man now looks after or regards. Oh <hi>England!</hi> where are now thy Wiſe Men? where are thy Pilots? where are thy Phyſicians? where are thy Counſelors? where are thy Hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers? where are they that pity thee, and ſay, <hi>Alas, Alas Poor England!</hi> thy Husband hath rejected thee, as a Wife of Whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms, and thou art become a Widow of Sorrows: thou art left as a Cottage in a Vineyard; <hi>as a Lodge in a Garden of Cucumbers, as a Beſieged City. Thy bruiſe is incureable, and thy wound is grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous. There is none left to plead thy Cauſe, that thou mighteſt be bound up: thou hast no healing Medicin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s left thee; Fear and a Snare and the Pit are upon thee, and to whom wilt thou ſtretch forth thy hands, to whom wilt thou lift up thy Voice for help?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thou waſt lately Rich and Flouriſhing Kingdom, and for thy Plenty, Wealth and Glory waſt both the Wonder and Envy of the World. Whilſt thou didſt enjoy the Preſence of God, through his Word and Ordinances; whilſt Iniquity was baniſh'd out of Publique View; whilſt Holineſs and Righteouſneſs, Juſtice and Judgment, Truth and Equity had their chief place in thee, <hi>Thou waſt a People ſaved by the Lord,</hi> Honoured by the Lord, Exalted,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:200387:23"/> Magnified, Protected by the Lord. <hi>Thou waſt the H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ad and not the Tail, even the Glory of Kingdoms and Nations.</hi> Our Land then, was bleſſed with the precious things of Heaven, with the dew and the deep that coutcheth beneath, with the precious fruits brought forth by the Sun, and with the precious things put forth by the Moon, with the precious things of the Earth, and the Fulneſs thereof. We had plenty of Gold, and of Jewels of fine Gold; and our Houſes were ſtored with Silver; our Barns and Store-houſes were repleniſhed, and we were plenteous in Goods; in the fruit of our Cattel, and in the fruit of our Ground. Our Sons were as Plants grown up in their Youth, our Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters as poliſht Pillars; our Oxen were ſtrong to labour, and our Sheep brought forth Thouſands: we did eat our Bread with joy, and drank our Wine with a merry heart, becauſe God accepted our Works. Yea then the Firſt-Born of the Poor did feed, and the Needy did ly down in Safety; for there was no breaking in nor going out, nor complaining in our Streets. We were a happy People that were in ſuch a caſe, yea much more happy, becauſe God was our Lord.</p>
            <p>And thou O <hi>London,</hi> (for my heart is towards thee, and I am diſtreſſed for thee O <hi>London,</hi> and pained at the very heart) Thou waſt a Joyous City, whoſe Antiquity was of Ancient Days; thou waſt the Crowning City, whoſe Merchants were Princes, whoſe Traff<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iquers were the Honourable of the Earth: by thy great Wiſdom, and by thy Traffique thou didſt get thee Riches, and thou didſt get Gold and Silver into thy Treaſuries. The Harveſt of the Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver was thy Revenue, and thou waſt the Mart of Nations. All Nations emptied their Delicacies into thy Boſom, and poured forth their pleaſant things into thy Lap. And when thy Wares went forth out of thy Seas, thou filledſt many People, thou didſt enrich the Kings of the Earth with the multitude of thy Riches, and of thy Merchandiſe. Thou waſt alſo the Mountain of God, thou hadſt, in the midſt of thee, the ſtones of Fire. Thou waſt the chief High-Place; the Miniſters of Jeſus were dear to thee, and thy Arms were always open to embrace them; thou didſt fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent the Solemn Aſſemblies of the Saints, with the Multitude of them that kept right Holy-Day. The Out-caſts of Chriſt were wont to dwell with thee, and thou waſt a Covert to them from the face of the Spoiler. Many Fatherleſs Children had harbour and ſuccour in thee, and thou waſt a Husband to the Widows. It was thy Meat and Drink to feed the hungry, and to cloath the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, and to viſit the Priſoners of Jeſus Chriſt. Thou waſt as the Vine-tree amongſt the Trees of the Foreſt, Verily a Noble Vine; But why haſt thou ſo ſuddenly turned into the Degenerate Plant of a Strange Vine? Why of a right Seed did you ſo eaſily be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come ſtrange Children, whoſe Mouth talketh Vanity, and your Right Hand is a Right Hand of Falſhood? Why didſt thou join thy ſelf with the Wicked, and help the Ungodly? Why didſt
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:200387:23"/> thou love them that hate the Lord, and didſt turn thy heart and hand againſt them that love the Lord? Thou didſt reject his Miniſters: thou didſt perſecute his People; thou didſt hunt the ſteps of the Righteous that they could not go in thy Streets; thou didſt hawll to Priſon the Aſſemblies of the Saints; and didſt make havock of the Church of Chriſt till there was no remedy.</p>
            <p>For when the Lord ſaw this he was angry, for he looked for Grapes from you, and you brought forth wild Grapes; he look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for Judgment from you, but behold Oppreſſion! for Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, but behold a Cry! <hi>Wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>refore he bent his Bow againſt thee like an Enemy, He ſtood with his Right Hand like an Adverſary.</hi> He ſent a Fire into the midſt of thee that could not be quenched, and it hath devoured thee, and brought thee to Aſhes on the Earth, in the ſight of all them that beheld thee. He hath ſwallowed up thy Habitations, he hath thrown down in his Wrath your plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant Dwellings, your ſtately and beautiful Buildings. He ſent into thee treacherous Dealers to deal treacherouſly with thee, and Spoilers to ſpoil thee; whilſt thou waſt become a ſilly Dove without heart. He hath brought upon thee the days that have not come on thee ſince thou waſt a City; He hath ſtained the Pride of thy Glory, and brought into contempt all thy Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Perſons: they that did feed delicately were left deſolate in the Streets; they that were brought up in Silks and Scarlet em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braced Dunghils: they that dwelt in well built Houſes were glad to ſhelter themſelves in Booths, and to crowd their heads in deſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late places; they are come down from their Glory to ſit in Duſt. For thy filthineſs was found in thy Skirts, therefore thou waſt brought down wonderfully. How are thy Merchandiſe of Gold and Silver, and Precious Stones, and of Pearl, and of fine Linnen, and Purple and Silk, thy broidered Works, thy Cheſts of rich Apparel, thy Spices and Odors, thy Veſſels of precious Wood, of Braſs and Iron, and Marble; thy Wine and Oil, thy ſtately Build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings and beautiful Structures of many Generations, how in three or four days are they all brought to nothing? <hi>London,</hi> the Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of the Kingdom, the Beauty of <hi>England's</hi> Excellency, is become as when God overthrew <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Gomorrah:</hi> and is now at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, a place for doleful Creatures, for Owls to dwell in, and for Satyrs to dance in, and for Wild Beaſts to cry among the deſolate Houſes, and Dragons in their Dwellings. For thou art ſwept with the Beſom of Deſtruction, and the Line of Emptineſs is ſtretched out upon thee; becauſe thou didſt reject the Word of the Lord, and kneweſt not the day of thy Viſitation.</p>
            <p>How art thou brought down, which waſt inhabited by Seafa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Men? the renowned City which waſt ſtrong at Sea? and thy Inhabitants did cauſe terrour to all Nations. All that knew thee formerly are aſtoniſht at thee; thou art become a Terror to them that ſee thee, and they that hear of thee are pained for thee. I was bowed down at the hearing of it, I was diſmayed at the ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:200387:24"/> of it. <hi>O Lord b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hold my affliction, for the Enemy hath magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied himſelf: ſee and conſider, for I am become Vile.</hi> Our Enemies ſay, This, this is the Day we have looked for; we have found it, we have ſeen it. This Day ſhall do that which the <hi>Fifth</hi> of <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vember</hi> could not do; now ſhall we ſee our deſire upon them; for the Strength of the <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Intereſt is broken; we have bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken the Head of it, and now ſhall we raſe it, to the very founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of it. But O Lord thou haſt ſeen my wrong, judge thou my Cauſe. Thou haſt ſeen all their Vengeance, and all their i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maginations againſt me; thou knoweſt the Contrivers, the Abet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, the Incouragers, the Actors, the Favourers of this Helliſh Miſchief; and all thoſe that rejoice in it: Give unto them All Sorrow of Heart, thy Curſe unto them. Perſecute and deſtroy them in Anger, from under the Heavens of the Lord. And let all the People ſay <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But now I muſt ſhake hands with thee O <hi>London</hi> in thy Duſt and Aſhes, for there is hope in this thy End. And I muſt turn my ſelf back again to <hi>England,</hi> the Land of my Nativity, and take up a Lamentation for it. O <hi>England,</hi> what Nation was like un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee from the Riſing of the Sun to the Setting thereof? thou waſt a People ſatisfied with favour, and full with the Bleſſings of the Lord, but art now ſuddenly become a poor and peeled People, meeted out and trodden down. Thou art ſmitten with a perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual ſtroke in anger, by a heavy hand: thou art oppreſſed, ſpoyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and cruſhed in pieces evermore, and there is no man to ſave thee. For God hath remembred our Iniquities againſt us, and ſet our ſins in the light of his Countenance. For by Lying, and Swea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, and Oppreſſing, and Slaying, and Drink<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng, and Whoring and Blaſpheming, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> the Land is defiled, under the Inhabitants thereof. We have forſaken the Laws of God, changed the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances of Chriſt, and broken the Everlaſting Covenant, and therefore hath the Curſe devoured us. Our Labours yield us no Profit: our Plowing, Sowing and Reaping eats up the Husband-Man: our Trade is every where decayed: our Gold and Silver are exhauſted and drained away: our Eſtates are impoveriſht and waſted: the Abundance we had gotten and laid up, is departed: our Exactions and Taxes are heavy upon us, ſo that we eat our Bread with ſorrow, and drink with ſighing; for they have found out our Riches as a Neſt, and as one gathereth Eggs that are left, ſo have they gathered the Subſtance of the Nation, and there was none that durſt move the Wing, or open the Mouth to the People. We are brought ſo low that we have forgotten Proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity; but we daily mourn and fade away; for we are filled with bitterneſs, and made drunk with Wormwood. For our Wiſe Counſellors are become Fools, Underſtanding is periſhed from them: our Princes are rebellious, and Companions of Thieves; they are Riotous Perſons that eat not for Strength but for Drunk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enneſs. Our Counſellors take Counſel, but not of God, but againſt
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:200387:24"/> him: our Judges abhor true Judgment, and pervert all Equity; they turn Judgment into Gall, and the fruit of Righteouſneſs into Hemlock: they juſtifie the Wicked for a Reward, and take away the righteouſneſs of the Righteous from him. Our Prieſts, of all Titles and Degrees, are like roaring Lions in the midſt of us, ravening the Prey; they rob the Purſes of Men; they im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſon their Bodies; they devour their Souls: they live in Riot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Drunkenneſs, they commit Adultery, and ſpeak Lyes: they ſtrengthen the hands of Evil Doers, that none doth return from his Wickedneſs. Our People are fooliſh and unwiſe, a company of treacherous Men, that ly in wait for precious Souls; they are perverſe Children, who have forſaken the Law of the Lord, and have ſaid to the Holy One of <hi>Iſrael, Depart from us.</hi> Wherefore we are become a baſe Kingdom, becauſe we have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected all righteouſneſs; yea, the baſeſt of Kingdoms, becauſe we have Apoſtatized from the Truth. Of a Pleaſant and Joyful Land, we are become a Land of Trouble and Anguiſh; where is the Young and Old Lion, the Viper and fiery flying Serpent. We are become a Mingled People, Strangers devour us in our preſence; they devour our Strength, they ſwallow up our Rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, they eat up our Bread; yea they deſtroy us, our Cities and Towns, and there is none to reprove them. We who were the chief of Nations, the Princeſs of Provinces, who when we ſpake there was trembling to the ends of the Earth, are now become weak and contemptible; becauſe our Rock hath ſold us, and the Lord hath ſhut us up, Therefore the Pomp of our Strength hath ceaſed, and our Spirit fails in the midſt of us. So that we are ſhamefully brought down, by the leaſt and loweſt of the Nations: who have ſubdued our Naval Power; taken, burnt and ſpoil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed our Royal Ships, the Wall and Bulwark of our Nation: fought us in our own Bowels; triumphed over us in our own River; blocked up the Paſſage of our chief City; ſtopped all intercourſe of Trade; made a Spoil of our Riches, and a Prey of our Merchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe; hindred and deprived us of all our pleaſant things; berea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved us of ſeveral of our Rich and Advantageous Plantations; brought us down to their feet, humbly to beg their favour, and have made us a Reproach, a Proverb and a Hiſſing to all Nations. O <hi>England</hi> who ſhall bewail thee? What Lamentations ſhall we take up for thee? Oh that thou wert ſenſible of thy Stroke and couldſt bewail thy ſelf, for thou haſt ſinned grievouſly, therefore art thou caſt out of the Mountain of the Lord, thou art caſt to the ground, and laid before Kings and Nations, that they may behold thee. This is the end of the Children of Pride; for they that exalt themſelves ſhall be made Low. And therefore <hi>talk no more ſo exceeding proudly, let not Arrogance come out of your Mouth again, for God is a God of Judgment, and by him actions are weighed. The Adverſaries of the Lord ſhall be broken in pieces: out of Heaven ſhall he thunder upon them, and therefore let not the Rebellious exalt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves,</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:200387:25"/>
            <p>Thus have I rehearſed the Evils we ly under; and now I ſhall repreſent ſome of the Great and Deadly Dangers that we are in.</p>
            <p>And one is, to have the Nation quite overrun with <hi>Popery,</hi> and to have the <hi>Popes Throne of Iniquity</hi> new erected amongſt us. And are there not ſwarms of <hi>Priests</hi> and <hi>Jeſuits</hi> earneſtly at work to bring this to paſs? they having emptied their <hi>Popiſh Cloyſters</hi> and <hi>Monaſteri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s</hi> from beyond Sea into <hi>England,</hi> to promote their <hi>Catholique Deſign</hi> here. And they knowing who ſtands at their right hand, have done it with great boldneſs, and with too great ſucceſs, For they have perverted not only very many of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon People, but ſome Nobility alſo, and many Gentry. And they have two great Engines to advance their deſign, to wit, on the one hand Safety, on the other Danger; on the one hand Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motion, on the other Deſtruction; on the one hand Life, on the other Death; with the one of them they allure, with the other they terrifie; with the one they draw whom they can with the other they drive whom they cannot draw. And theſe Engines are of that force, that thereby they have conquered many weak, ſinful and unſtable Souls, yea and have prevailed with ſome Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of Honour and Quality, to ſend their Sons to Monaſteries, and their Daughters to Nunneries beyond Sea, to be trained up in their Damnable Religion there, till better proviſion can be made for them here; of which they now are in full hopes.</p>
            <p>And now think with your ſelves, and conſider well, O my Dear <hi>Protestant</hi> Country-Men, how could you endure to ſee the <hi>Pope</hi> Worſhipped here again in <hi>England,</hi> for a God on Earth? to ſee him ſet his proud Foot on the Neck of your King? to ſee your King a Tributary to the <hi>Pope,</hi> and to ſtand or fall at his baſe plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure? how could you indure to be forced to acknowledge his ſinful and fooliſh Decrees to be equal to the Holy Word of God? and to own his little Wafer, or piece of Bread, for the very Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Body and Bloud of Chriſt which was crucified and ſhed on the Croſs? how could you indure to have your throats ſtretched ſo wide, as to ſwallow down only this one Abomination of his, which is more vaſt and rude than the firſt Chaos? how could you indure to ſee new Roods erected in every Pariſh Church? and to bow your ſelves down and worſhip Stocks and Stones, Cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fixes and Images, inſtead of the True and Living God? how could you frame your ſelves to Auricular Confeſſion, and to rehearſe or enumerate all your ſins in a Prieſts Ear, who himſelf ſtands in need of Forgiveneſs more than you, being a greater Sinner? how could you indure that their luſty Prieſts ſhould defile your Wives and Daughters, they being prohibited Wives of their own; and ſo ſhould drive again a General Trade of Whoredom in the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as they have been wont to do formerly? how could you ſubmit your ſelves to their <hi>Popiſh</hi> Pennance, and to travel their <hi>Popiſh</hi> Pilgrimages, to their feigned Saints and ridiculous Reliques?
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:200387:25"/> how could you bear the ſeverity of their Eccleſiaſtical Courts and Cenſures, and to be pronounced Heretiques by thoſe who are themſelves the greateſt Heretiques in the World? how could You Noblemen and Gentlemen, who have your Eſtates, or part of them, in Abbey and Church-Lands, as they were called, be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to have them taken away from You and your Poſterity, and given back again to maintain <hi>Abbots, Monks, Friers, Nuns</hi> and ſuch kind of <hi>Popiſh Vermin</hi> and <hi>Locuſts,</hi> which, if once admitted, will eat up again every green thing in the Land? And let me tell you, that all theſe Eſtates of yours, they do not only promiſe to themſelves, but verily expect them. Yea farther, how could you indure to have your loving Husbands taken from your Heads, and your dear Wives torn out of your Boſoms, your ſweet Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren dragg'd out of your Houſes, your near Relations and friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Neighbours hawlled and hurried into Priſons and Dungeons, and there to be wracked, ſtarved, tormented, and at laſt (if they live to it) to be put alive into the flames of Fire, there to be burnt and conſumed to Aſhes? and that only becauſe they ſincerely cleave to Chriſt and his Goſpel, and will not adhere to <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> nor receive his Mark, nor do his Helliſh Drudgery? how could you indure to ſee this cruel Beaſt of <hi>Rome</hi> to play <hi>Rex</hi> here in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> again; and though he be the Firſt-Born of the Devil, yet to ſet himſelf up above all that is called God, and Worſhipped? And yet you are now in more danger to ſee all theſe things come to paſs (<hi>becauſe you received not the truth in the love of it,</hi> whilſt you enjoyed it) than your Predeceſſors have been this Hundred Years, they having now gotten both Wind and Tide with them, even <hi>Opportunity</hi> and <hi>Incouragement.</hi> Wherefore a Great Man conclud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, <hi>That now certainly the</hi> Papiſts <hi>would do their Work,</hi> they were in ſo fair a way. But he reckoned without his Hoaſt. And leſt my <hi>Proteſtant Country-Men</hi> ſhould be too much diſcouraged in this apparent and approaching Danger, I will furniſh you with one Rich Cordial, out of the Words of <hi>Henry</hi> the VIII. which he directed to the <hi>Papiſts</hi> in his days, in his foregoing Declaration againſt them: where he ſaith, <hi>Are you not wicked which ſo hate the Truth, that except ſhe be utterly baniſhed, ye will never ceaſe to vex her? The Living God is alive, neither can Truth his Darling, He be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing alive, be called to ſo great ſhame, contumely and injury as you would have her; and if ſhe may be called to all theſe, yet can ſhe come to none of them. Who is he that grievouſly lamenteth not! Men to be come to ſuch Shameleſs Boldneſs, to ſhew apertly that they be Enemies to Chriſt himſelf? on the other ſide, who would not be glad to ſee ſuch Men, as fooliſh as they be Wicked?</hi> For they work a deceitful Work, and by all their cunning Craftineſs, Myſterious, and Induſtrious Actings, they only dig the Pit, <hi>into which they muſt fall themſelves,</hi> and contrive the ruine that muſt be their own Portion.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:200387:26"/>
            <p>Your Second Danger, is to have the moſt Cruel and Inhumane Maſſacre executed upon you, that ever yet was committed in the World, by the Conſecrated Hands and Weapons of the <hi>Papiſts.</hi> And this Glorious Service of theirs is deſigned upon the <hi>Engliſh Proteſtants,</hi> for the ſingular Promotion of the <hi>Catholique</hi> Cauſe, which hath its way uſually prepared into all Nations, by Fire and Sword. The Wrath of the <hi>Papiſts</hi> is ſo kindled againſt you, and they are ſo thoroughly ſet on fire from Hell, that they are ready to break forth into their greateſt flames, and to endeavour the Deſtruction of All at Once. It is well known, how well they are Hors'd and Arm'd, and how they train their Troops againſt the Bloudy Day intended. It is well known, how well they are furniſh'd with Money, intended for other purpoſes. It is well known what numbers of <hi>French Men</hi> are brought into the bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els of the <hi>Engliſh;</hi> and many Noblemen and Gentlemen are ſo pleaſed with the Children of thoſe Strangers, that they have <hi>French</hi> Servants, <hi>Papists,</hi> to attend them, whom they have well Mounted and Armed, enough to make a little Army of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. And this they do that their ſtrength may be hidden till opportunity ſhall ſerve to make it appear. It is well known that the chief Places of Strength, and many Chief Commands are in the hands of <hi>Papiſts.</hi> And now they become ſo numerous, and having ſuch power, what is there wanting but a convenient Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity to fulfil all that is in their Hearts, upon Secure, Unar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, Unprepared People, and to diſpatch their work in few days, and eſpecially upon thee O <hi>London,</hi> who art their chiefeſt Eye-Sore. <hi>O England,</hi> (except the Lord prevent it) thy Calamity is near, at the very Door: and thou mayſt expect every day, now Peace is made Abroad, when theſe will unſheath and draw their Swords upon you here at Home: and you muſt be charg'd in the Kings Name (for ſo they will abuſe it) to ſtand ſtill, and to hold forth your Throats to Murderers. You cannot forget the dreadful Maſſacre at <hi>Paris,</hi> nor that late more dreadful and blou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy Maſſacre of the <hi>Engliſh Proteſtants</hi> in <hi>Ireland,</hi> when more than a Hundred Thouſand Innocent Perſons, Men, Women and Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren were in a very ſhort time, with the greateſt Cruelties and Torments that ever were heard of, murdered by them; and what Authority they pretended for it. But they have treaſured up in their minds the fulneſs of all Cruelties, for you <hi>Engliſh-men.</hi> They have diſcovered ſomething of their Kindneſs and good Pleaſure to you in their firing the City of <hi>London,</hi> which they have left as an Everlaſting Monument of their Treachery and Villany to <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and of their hatred to <hi>Engliſh Proteſtants;</hi> and let this moſt notorious fact of theirs be engraven in great Characters on the Gates and Walls, and Chief Places of your City, when it ſhall be built again; that all Poſterity when they ſhall ſee New <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> may know and conſider what Perſons, and what Religion burnt the Old. They have alſo often attempted the firing of
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:200387:26"/> 
               <hi>Southwark,</hi> and of the remaining parts of the City; for nothing but the utter ruine of it will ſatisfie them. And when the kindl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of ſome of theſe later flames, was related to a Great Perſon, they laughing ſaid, <hi>Now the Game is begun again:</hi> for they make but a <hi>May game</hi> of conſuming all. And yet Fire only will not ſatisfie them, it is bloud muſt follow, or they are never the near. It is you <hi>O Engliſh Proteſtants,</hi> whoſe lives they thirſt after, and they can neither eat nor drink comfortably, nor ſleep quietly, till they be filled with this Veniſon. And therefore of you it may be truly ſaid, <hi>Your lives are in jeopardy every hour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yet for all this let us not deſpond nor caſt away our Confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, ſaying, <hi>Our hope is cut off, and we are periſhed;</hi> for he that ſits in Heaven laughs them to ſcorn, even the Lord hath them in Deriſion: and though we hold our peace, he will ſpeak to them in his Wrath, and vex them in his ſore diſpleaſure. He will make his Arrows drunk with their bloud, and his Sword ſhall devour their fleſh, from the beginning of Revenges upon the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my. <hi>Rejoice O ye Nations, with his Paople, for he will av<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nge the Bloud of his Servants, and will render V<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ng ance to his Adverſaries, and will be m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rciful to his Land, and to his People.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Another of your Dangers, which alſo is one of the greateſt, is your own Heedleſneſs and ſtrange Security, in the midſt of ſuch thick Clouds and Storms which have encompaſſed us round, able to awaken even dead Men. How ſtupid and ſott<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh were you at the burning of your City, when you ſaw with your own eies, your Houſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, your Subſtance, your Riches, all conſuming together in thoſe furious flames before your faces; yet how inſenſible were you of your deplorable condition? how regardleſs of that heavy hand of God? how inſenſible of the Treachery and Cruelty of Men? who did not only begin thoſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>mes, but alſo continue them in the Progreſs they had appointed for t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>em. Had you the Brains or Hearts of Men, to ſuffer thoſe Incendiaries who were taken in the very Act, to be reſcued from Juſtice, and releaſed to carry on their Villany again? ſurely you were ſo Sottiſh, that had not the Lord been the more merciful to you, your Lives and Houſes had periſhed together, as it was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned. Moreover, how inſenſible have you been of the <hi>Popiſh Plot,</hi> and intended Maſſacre; as if thoſe good Men had been but in Jeſt, when a Regiment of <hi>Papiſts</hi> was brought up to ſecure the <hi>Prot<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſtants,</hi> and a company of Wolves to guard the Flock; and when ſome of their own Pens and Lips reveal their minds, why ſhould you yet be ſo ignorant of it, who are wholly concerned in it? Wherefore as your Lives hitherto have been dear to God, ſo let them now alſo be dear to your ſelves, and do not you ſay, <hi>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ace, Peace,</hi> when the <hi>Papiſts</hi> intend and prepare <hi>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſtruction, Deſtruction;</hi> but let that be verified of you, which <hi>Henry</hi> VIII. ſaith of his time; to wit, <hi>The World is not now in ſo light a ſuſpici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of you</hi> (Papiſts) <hi>as it hath been hitherto; but every Man ſeeth
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:200387:27"/> before his Eies, your deceits, your Wicked Minds, your Immortal Hatred againſt the Truth, and the Profeſſors af it, every Man ſees how many miſerable Tragedies your pretence of an Unity and Concord hath brought into</hi> Chriſtendom. <hi>They ſee your fair face of Peace hath ſerved Sedition, and troubled almoſt all Chriſtian Realms.</hi> And therefore ſeeing they were ſo quick-ſighted who lived above an hundred and thirty years ago, to ſee and foreſee the Treache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries and Cruelties of the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> let not us who live ſo many years after, and have had far greater experience of them, be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together blind, and ſee nothing at all, in the clear Noon-ſhine of their Doings.</p>
            <p>Wherefore let all be admoniſhed, that after the deſired Tidings of Peace they be not ſo eagerly addicted to the rebuilding their Houſes, and regaining their Trade, and proſecuting their World<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Affairs and Concernments (whilſt yet they are uncertain of the enjoyment of any thing) that they become careleſs and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gardleſs how it fares with the Church of Chriſt and his Goſpel (which is the very light and life of our Souls, as well as the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of all our outward comforts) or how active and watchful the Brood of <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> which lurks amongſt us, becomes, that they may deprive us of our Religion and Lives; and ſo, be as greedy Birds that are ſcratching for food, whilſt the Net is ſprea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding over them to catch them at unawares, for what will it profit you to win Eſtates, and to loſe your Lives? your Lives are better than your Eſtates; and your Eſtates are but for the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of your Lives. And if the Enemy take away your Lives, whoſe ſhall your Eſtates be? they ſhall even become a reward to the Murderers.</p>
            <p>Awaken therefore O <hi>Proteſtants</hi> and <hi>Engliſh</hi> Men out of your deep and dangerous Security! and ſtand upon your feet like Men: Ye dead men live again, and I will humbly and faithfully adviſe you (as I am able) out of very love, in a few things.</p>
            <p n="1">1. My <hi>Firſt</hi> Advice is, that you believe none of their pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed fairneſs and kindneſs to you, ſeeing their hearts are wholly againſt you, and their hatred to you is immortal; even the ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred of the Devil in the Hearts of Men, which is a certain fire of Hell which goes not out by Day or by Night. But know for cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, when they promiſe fair, they are not to perform any thing, but the quite contrary: when they ſeem to kiſs you, they intend to kill you; when they ſuffer you to be quite, 'tis that they may bring the greater Trouble upon you; when they retreat from the exerciſe of their fierceneſs, 'tis that they return upon you with the greater Fury, when you ſhall leſs think of it; for their whole Trade is <hi>Deceit</hi> and <hi>Violence.</hi> Though Satan transform himſelf into an <hi>Angel of Light,</hi> yet ſtill is he is the <hi>Prince of Darkneſs;</hi> and theſe his Followers are exactly like him, both to deceive and to deſtroy: they will change their Colours, like <hi>Proteus,</hi> to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:200387:27"/> you, but they will never change their cruel Minds; but they that will be deceived, let them be deceived.</p>
            <p n="2">2. My <hi>Second</hi> Advice is, that none either Plot or Attempt any thing againſt the preſent Power, but that all ſtand ſtill in their Place and Calling, like Wiſemen with their Eies in their Head, quietly waiting for the Salvation of God. For no Mans Hands can help him in this Matter, but our ſtrength is to ſit ſtill. We can no more change Kingdoms and Governments in the World, than we can alter the Courſe of the Sun or Moon in the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens; but it is the Great God that muſt do theſe great things. It is the moſt High God that reigns in the Kingdom of Men, and gives them to whomſoever he will. And when his time is come, the ſet and full time, and the moſt High ſhall utter his Voice, his inſtruments ſhall be at his foot, ready to do his work, even to execute the Vengeance written; and all his mighty Providences ſhall concur, to bring about the Council of his Will. Wherefore remember that Mans raſhneſs carrys ruin in it, but Patience per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects both Gods Works and Mans. <hi>In Patience poſſeſs your Souls.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherefore all that we would do, if we might be heard by thoſe that are inſtructed to help, at this needful Time is, only to deſire for the Glory of God, and the Nations good, and their own, theſe three things.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That the dear and precious Goſpel of our Lord and Saviour may be permitted publiquely to be Preached again, in the Purity and Power of it, and that the faithful Teachers may be reſtored to their Miniſtry throughout the whole Nation. For when Jeſus Chriſt who <hi>hath all Power in Heaven and Earth given into his hands,</hi> hath commanded his Miniſters to <hi>go and teach in all Nations.</hi> How can you Worldly Powers, who have but a little Power in this Nation, anſwer it to him, when you forbid that to be done which he hath ſo ſolemnly commanded? He that <hi>hath all Power in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and Earth</hi> hath commanded his Miniſters to teach his Goſpel, and dare you who have but a little power on Earth, and none at all in Heaven forbid them? If you do not repent of and amend this our Evils, it had been better for you, that you had never been born.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Our ſecond deſire is, That all <hi>Popiſh</hi> Commanders may be Disbanded, and put out of all Office and Truſt in a <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Nation; and that all <hi>Papiſts</hi> through <hi>England</hi> may be diſarmed; ſeeing they are not armed for us, but againſt us.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That all <hi>French</hi> and <hi>Outlandiſh</hi> Men may be baniſhed; for they are but Moths in our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Garment, to fret it by degrees, all to pieces; as they have fretted a great deal of it already.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:200387:28"/>
            <p>And what <hi>Engliſh-man</hi> or <hi>Proteſtant</hi> is there, that wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> not ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> with us in theſe neceſſary Deſires, which if they be not granted, farewel all Good Days from <hi>England</hi> for our time.</p>
            <p>And now to conclude all, I ſhall only leave two or three Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Antidotes with my dear Country-Men to preſerve them from the noyſome Contagion and Plague of <hi>Popery.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Conſider with Trembling, that none are given up to this Damnable Deluſion but thoſe whoſe Names are not Written in the <hi>Lambs Book of Life,</hi> as the Spirit of God affirms <hi>Rev.</hi> 13.8. ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>And all that dwell upon Earth ſhall worſhip him (i. e.</hi> the Beaſt or Antichriſt of <hi>Rome) whoſe Names are not writt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n in the Book of Life, of the Lamb ſlain from the Foundation of the World,</hi> And what Perſon would carry ſuch a Worm in his Conſcience continually, for the whole World, and all the Kingdoms and Gl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>y of it, as to know and certainly to underſtand, that his Name <hi>is not written in the Book of Life,</hi> nor can ever be put in; for all the Writings in that Book are from Eternity, and no new thing can be inſerted in it. And therefore let Men ſay what they will, they are none of Gods Elect, who cloſe in with this Falſe and H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>tical Religion, after the Goſpel hath been Preached to them, and they have been inſtructed in it. For to depart from the known Truth to known Error, is not a Sin of Ignorance, but of Malice; and this is the <hi>Sin unto Death,</hi> for which there is no Remiſſion. Wherefore let every one that would attain to any comfortable Aſſurance that his Name is Written in the <hi>Book of Life,</hi> flee from <hi>Popery.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. They that Apoſtatiſe to this Falſe Religion, are a ſurely to be Damn'd as if they were in Hell already, This is a hard ſaying, but a True One: as it is evident in that of <hi>Paul,</hi> 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2. where ſpeaking of <hi>Antichrist,</hi> that <hi>Wicked One, whoſe coming is after the working of Satan. with all Pow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r and Signs, and Lying Won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, and with all deceiveableneſs of Unrighteouſneſs in them that periſh, becauſe they received not the love of the Truth, that they might be ſaved.</hi> He adds, <hi>And for this cauſe God ſhall ſend th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m ſtrong Deluſions that they ſhould b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lieve a Lye, that</hi> they All may be Damn'd <hi>that b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lieve not the Truth, but have pleaſure in Unright<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ouſneſs.</hi> This ſort of People God gives them up to believe a Lye, the Grand Lye of <hi>Popery</hi> (for this whole Religion is nothing elſe but one continued Lye, from the beginning to the end of it) to the intent, that they ſhould all Periſh and be Damn'd. This is the Word of God, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all wilful <hi>Papists,</hi> and it cannot be made void. <hi>John</hi> alſo teſtifies <hi>Rev.</hi> 14.9. that an Angel Proclaimed with a loud voice, ſaying, <hi>If any Man Worſhip the Beaſt and his Image, and receive his Mark in his Forehead, or in his hand, the ſame ſhall drink of the Wine of the Wrath of God which is poured out without mixture into the Cup of his Indignation. and he ſhall be tormented with Fire and Brimstone, in the preſence of the holy Angels, and in the preſence of the Lamb;
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:200387:28"/> and the Smoak of their Torment aſc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ndeth up for ever and ever: and they have no reſt Day nor Night, which Worſhip the Beaſt and his Image, and whoſoever receiveth the Mark of his Name.</hi> In which Scripture you may ſee with open face, the ſad end of all the <hi>Popiſh</hi> Genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: which is to be <hi>tormented for ever and ever.</hi> Wherefore out of very Malice, they have been, are, and will be our Tormentors here, when they get opportunity, becauſe the Devil is to be their Tormentor in Hell for ever. Wherefore who ever would avoid the Torments of Hell let him fly from <hi>Popery.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Laſtly <hi>Antichriſt</hi> is now in his Old Age, and draws near his End, yea is drawing his laſt breath. He is very ſhortly to be ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly deſtroyed with the Spirit of Chriſts Mouth, and the Bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of his coming. And what Wiſe-Man, yea what Man of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon reaſon would join himſelf to <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> for one hour, yea for one quarter or minute of his hour? If Men might have reign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with him many years, and have enjoyed his Delicacies for a long Seaſon, then might it have been a ſtrong inducement to a carnal heart, who ſeeks his Portion only in this life, to have cloſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in with him; but now to do it when his Deſtruction draws near, what extream Folly and Madneſs muſt it needs be? Who would venture a Board that Ship which is juſt a ſinking? or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a Subject in that Kingdom which is juſt ready to be rooted up? and confident I am through God, that after Antichriſt and his Brood of Serpents, have play'd a few more of their old cruel Pranks anew in <hi>England,</hi> both He and They will become ſo ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly odious to All, that their Name ſhall be no more remembred among us, but with higheſt Contempt and Indignation, and that for ever. And let the Lord ſay <hi>Amen,</hi> and all his People.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="conclusion">
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:200387:29"/>
            <p>AND now O Lord, to whom ſhould we look? our Eies are only unto thee. And we beſeech thee to look down from Heaven, the Habitation of thy Holineſs, and of thy Glory, upon us, and upon our preſent Sad, and almoſt Deſperate Condition: and ſtretch forth thy Holy Arm to maintain Thine Own Good Cauſe, (which thine Enemies ſcorn and deride, and laugh at among them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves) and to help afflicted Righteouſneſs, and thine own poor People, who are brought very low, ſo that their belly cleaveth, even to the duſt. Indeed, Vain is the Help of Man, and our Enemies ſay, <hi>There is no help for us in God:</hi> But yet we know there is help in thee, and that thy help is never in vain. For thou canst do the greateſt Things by the ſmalleſt Means, yea thou canſt do the greateſt Things, without all Means. For thou ſpakeſt and the World was made, thou didſt command, and it ſtood faſt. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore our Eies are unto thee, O Lord, and we do believe that thou canſt do all things; and can ſo do them, that none can reſiſt thee. <hi>Is any thing too hard for the Lord?</hi> ſhall we call thy Power in Queſtion, who didst prepare a ſafe paſſage for thy People through the mighty Waters, and didſt cauſe them to walk on dry ground through the depths of the Sea? Take therefore thy great Power and come and Reign in the midſt of theſe thy greateſt Enemies, till thou make them All thy Footſtool, and till thou hast put down all Rule, Authority and Power which lifts up its Head, and ſtretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth forth its Arm againſt thee, O Lord, and thy Holy and Bleſſed Gospel, and thine Anointed. Oh cauſe Iniquity to stop its Mouth, and Wickedneſs to hide its face again. Let Violence no more be heard in our Land, nor Waſting and Destruction within our Bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders; let the cauſe of the Fatherleſs and of the Widows be juſtly judged, Let thy Priſoners be looſed, and thine oppreſſed be eaſed; let them be helped, who have no helper. Make way with thy ſtrong Arm for thy own <hi>Labourers</hi> to continue to come to <hi>thy Harveſt-Work;</hi> for thy Harveſt (we truſt) is very great in <hi>England.</hi> And therefore O Thou into whoſe hands all Things are delivered of the Father, and all Power in Heaven and Earth is given; and who by this Greateſt and Higheſt Authority of Thine, haſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded thy Miniſters, to go and teach all Nations, after thou didſt ſend them: Oh do thou make way for them to teach this Unworthy Nation, before the Coming of the Son of Man; that through their
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:200387:29"/> ministring thy Word, thy Church may awake and rouze up it ſelf, and put off its filthy Raiment, and may be reſtored to the Bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of its first riſing, when it was full of faith and love, and all Graces and Gifts of the Holy Ghoſt, without any mixture of <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian</hi> Errors, that all thy People may ſtrive together for the Faith of the Gospel, and not quarrel any longer about empty Forms; but may with One Mind, and with One Mouth confeſs the Truth as it is in <hi>Jeſus:</hi> and then ſhall all Kings bow down before thee, and all Nations that ſerve Thee, they ſhall ſing forth the Honour of thy Name and make thy Praiſe Glorious. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
